<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hope of Israel: written by Menasseh ben Israel, a Hebrew divine, and philosopher. Newly extant, and printed in Amsterdam, and dedicated by the author to the High Court, the Parliament of England, and to the Councell of State. Translated into English, and published by authority. In this treatise is shewed the place wherein the ten tribes at this present are, proved partly by the strange relation of one Anthony Montezinus, a Jew, of what befell him as he travelled over the Mountaines Cordillære, with divers other particulars about the restoration of the Jewes, and the time when.</title>
            <title>Miḳṿeh Yiśraʼel. English</title>
            <author>Manasseh ben Israel, 1604-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89453</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1350_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18014</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860324</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860324</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112444</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89453)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112444)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 178:E1350[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hope of Israel: written by Menasseh ben Israel, a Hebrew divine, and philosopher. Newly extant, and printed in Amsterdam, and dedicated by the author to the High Court, the Parliament of England, and to the Councell of State. Translated into English, and published by authority. In this treatise is shewed the place wherein the ten tribes at this present are, proved partly by the strange relation of one Anthony Montezinus, a Jew, of what befell him as he travelled over the Mountaines Cordillære, with divers other particulars about the restoration of the Jewes, and the time when.</title>
                  <title>Miḳṿeh Yiśraʼel. English</title>
                  <author>Manasseh ben Israel, 1604-1657.</author>
                  <author>Wall, Moses.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 90 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by R.I. for Hannah Allen, at the Crown in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Miḳṿeh Yiśraʼel by Moses Wall. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 4th".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library (Thomason Tracts) and the Harvard University Library (Early English books).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lost tribes of Israel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jews --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112444:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>HOPE</hi> of <hi>ISRAEL:</hi> Written By MENASSEH BEN ISRAEL, an Hebrew Divine, and Philoſopher.</p>
            <p>Newly extant, and Printed in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and Dedicated by the Author to the High Court, the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and to the Councell of State.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <p>In this Treatiſe is ſhewed the place wherein the ten Tribes at this preſent are, proved partly by the ſtrange relation of one <hi>Antony Monte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zinus,</hi> a <hi>Jew,</hi> of what befell him as he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled over the Mountaines <hi>Cordillaere,</hi> with divers other particulars about the reſtoratiòn of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and the time when.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>R. I.</hi> for <hi>Hannah Allen,</hi> at the Crown in Popeſ-head Alley, 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:112444:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112444:2"/>
            <head>To the Parliament, the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Court of <hi>England,</hi> and to the right Honourable the Councell of State, <hi>Menaſſeh Ben Iſraell,</hi> prayes God to give health, and all Happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not one cauſe alone (moſt renowned Fathers) which u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to move thoſe, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire by their Meditations to benefit Mankind, and to make them come forth in publique, to dedicate their Books to great Men; for ſome, and thoſe the moſt, are incited by Covetouſneſſe, that they may get money by ſo doing, or ſome peice of plate of Gold, or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; ſometimes alſo that they may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine their votes, and ſuffrages to get ſome place for themſelves, or their friends. But ſome are moved thereto,
<pb facs="tcp:112444:3"/>by meere and pure friendſhip, that ſo they may publickly teſtifie that love, and affection, which they beare them, whoſe names they prefixe to their Books; let the one, and the other, pleaſe themſelves, according as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the reaſon of the Dedication, whether it be good, or bad; for my part, I beſt like them, who doe it upon this ground, that they may not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend themſelves, or theirs, but what is for publick good.</p>
            <p>As for me (moſt renowned Fathers) in my dedicating this Diſcourſe to you I can truly affirme, that I am induced to it upon no other ground then this, that I may gaine your favour and good will to our Nation, now ſcattered almoſt all over the earth; neither thinke that I doe this, as if I were ignorant how much you have hitherto favoured our Nation; for it is made knowne to me, and to others of our Nation, by them who are ſo happy as neare at hand, to
<pb facs="tcp:112444:3"/>obſerve your apprehenſions, that ye doe vouchſafe to help us, not only by your prayers; yea, this hath compelled me to ſpeak to ye publickly, and to give ye thanks for that your charitable affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards us, and not ſuch thankes which come only from the tongue, but as are conceived by a gratefull minde.</p>
            <p>Give me leave therefore (moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Fathers) to ſupplicate ye, that ye would ſtill favour our good, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther love us. Truly, we men doe draw ſo much the nearer to Divine nature, when by how much we increaſe, by ſo much we cheriſh, and defend the ſmall, and weake ones; and with how much diligence doe you performe this, moſt renowned Fathers? who though ye ſeeme to be arrived to the higheſt top of felicity, yet ye doe not only not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe inferiour men, but ye ſo wiſh well to them, that ye ſeeme ſenſible of their calamity; ye knowing how acceptable to God ye are by ſo doing, who loves
<pb facs="tcp:112444:4"/>to doe good to them who doe good. And truly it is from hence, that of late ye have done ſo great things valiantly, and by an unuſuall attempt, and things much to be obſerved among the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The whole world ſtands amazed at theſe things, and the eyes of all are turned upon ye, that they may ſee whither all theſe things do tend, which the great Governour of all things ſeems to bring upon the world by ſo great changes, ſo famouſly remarkable, of ſo many Nations; and ſo all thoſe things which God is pleaſed to have fore-told by the Prophets, doe, and ſhall obtaine their accompliſhment. All which things of neceſſity muſt be fulfilled, that ſo <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> at laſt being brought back to his owne place; peace, which is promiſed under the Meſſiah, may be reſtored to the world; &amp; concord, which is the only Mother of all good things. Theſe things I handle more largely in this Treatiſe, which I dedicate to ye (moſt renowned
<pb facs="tcp:112444:4"/>Fathers) ye cannot be ignorant, that it is not only not unprofitable, but very uſefull for States, and Stateſ-men, to fore-ſee the iſſue (which yet is ever in Gods hand) of humane Counſels, that ſo they may obſerve, and underſtand from Divine truth, the events of things to come, which God hath determined by his Spirit in his holy Prophets. I know that this my labour will not be unacceptable to ye, how meane ſoever it be, which I truſt ye will cheerfully receive, becauſe that ye love our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as part of it, the Author of this Diſcourſe. But I entreat you be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that I pour out continuall prayers to God for your happineſſe. Farewell, moſt renowned Fathers, and flouriſh moſt proſperouſly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Menaſſeh Ben Iſrael.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112444:5"/>
            <head>MENASSEH BEN ISRAEL to the courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are, as many mindes as men, about the originall of the people of <hi>America,</hi> and of the firſt inhabitants of the new World, and of the <hi>Weſt-Indies;</hi> for how many men ſoever they were, or are, they came of thoſe two, <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>Eve;</hi> and conſequently of <hi>Noah,</hi> after the Floud. But that new World doth ſeeme wholly ſeparated from the old, therefore it muſt be that ſome did paſſe thither out of one (at leaſt) of the three parts of the World, ſc. <hi>Europe, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Africa;</hi> but the doubt is, what people were thoſe, and out of what place they went. Truly, the truth of that muſt be gathered, partly out of the ancient Hiſtories, and partly from conjectures; as their Habit, their Language, their Manners, which yet doe vary according to mens diſpoſitions; ſo that it is hard to finde out the certainty. Almost all who have viewed thoſe Countries, with great diligence, have been of different judgements: Some would have the praiſe of finding out <hi>Ame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> to be due to the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> others to the <hi>Phenicians,</hi> or the <hi>Canaanites;</hi> others to
<pb facs="tcp:112444:5"/>the <hi>Indians,</hi> or people of <hi>China;</hi> others to them of <hi>Norway,</hi> others to the inhabitants of the <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantick Iſlands,</hi> others to the <hi>Tartarians,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the ten Tribes. Indeed, every one grounds his opinion not upon probable arguments, but high conjectures, as will appeare farther by this Booke. But I having curiouſly examined what ever hath hitherto been writ upon this Subject, doe finde no opinion more probable, nor agreeable to reaſon, than that of our <hi>Montezinus,</hi> who ſaith, that the firſt inhabitants of <hi>America,</hi> were the ten Tribes of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whom the <hi>Tartarians</hi> conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and drove away; who after that (as God would have it) hid themſelves behind the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines <hi>Cordillerae.</hi> I alſo ſhew, that as they were not driven out at once from their Country, ſo alſo they were ſcattered into divers Provinces, ſc. into <hi>America,</hi> into <hi>Tartary,</hi> into <hi>China,</hi> into <hi>Media,</hi> to the Sabbaticall River, and into <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia.</hi> I prove that the ten Tribes never retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the ſecond Temple, that they yet keep the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and our ſacred Rites; and at laſt ſhall returne into their Land, with the two Tribes, <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Benjamin;</hi> and ſhall be governed by one Prince, who is <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Son of <hi>David;</hi> and without doubt that happy time is near, which I make appear by divers things; where, Reader, thou ſhalt finde divers Hiſtories worthy of memory, and many Propheſies of the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets
<pb facs="tcp:112444:6"/>opened, with much ſtudy, and care. I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly leave it to the judgement of the godly, and learned, what worth there is in this my Booke, and what my owne Nation owes me for my paines: It is called, <hi>The Hope of Iſrael;</hi> which name is taken from <hi>Jerem. 14.8.</hi> O the hope of Iſrael, the Saviour thereof. For the ſcope of this Diſcourſe is, to ſhow, that the hope in which we live, of the comming of the Meſſiah, is of a future, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, but infallible good, becauſe it is grounded upon the abſolute Promiſe of the bleſſed God.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I intend a continuation of <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> his Hiſtory of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> our famous Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian; I entreat, and beſeech all Learned men, in what part of the World ſoever they live (to whom I hope that ſhortly this Diſcourſe will come) that if they have any thing worthy of poſterity, that they would give me notice of it in time; for though I have collected many Acts of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and many Hiſtories out of the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> the <hi>Arabians,</hi> the <hi>Grecians,</hi> the Latines, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Authors of other Nations; yet I want many things for this my enterpriſe, all which I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to performe, that I may pleaſe my Nation; but rather to the glory of the bleſſed God, whoſe Kingdome is everlaſting, and his Word in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112444:6"/>
            <head>The Tranſlator to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Diſcourſe of a Jew comming to my hand, and having peruſed it, I thought it not inconvenient to make it ſpeake <hi>Engliſh;</hi> for the benefit of my Country-men, who wait for the redemption of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and at the ſame time, of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo. That the Author is a <hi>Jew,</hi> ought to be no ſcandall to us (though ſome of us Chriſtian <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> are ignorant of, and ſcandalized at the notion of the converſion of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> as the <hi>Iewes</hi> of old were, concerning our being Converted, and grafted into the true Stock, as in <hi>Acts</hi> 11.3.) for though God hath rejected them, yet not for ever, <hi>Romans</hi> 11.25, 26. And alſo the many Propheſies both in the Old, and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, which concerne their being recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb facs="tcp:112444:7"/>againe to grace, gathered from their diſperſion, and ſetled in their owne Land; and their flouriſhing eſtate under, now our, and then their and our Prince, Jeſus Chriſt the Meſſiah, who will then triumph glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, and all the people with him; theſe and many more Promiſes would want a fulfilling (which the God of Truth will never ſuffer) if there ſhould not be the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of a time, in which they ſhall be converted, and grace and peace be poured out upon <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles;</hi> though firſt upon the <hi>Iew,</hi> then the <hi>Gentile.</hi> But beſide this, the Author expreſſeth ſo much learning, that he deſerveth honour of all; ſo much ingenuity, and (ſo farre as his light reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) ſo great a meaſure of the knowledge and feare of God, that he may well be ſet for a patterne to us Chriſtians, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe much better than he, but live much worſe. One thing is very remarkable in him, that whereas many of us (like them who cannot ſee Wood for Trees) though Invironed with mercies in theſe late revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, (I ſpeake not to them who mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure mercies only, or chiefly, by plentifull tables, full purſes, rich accoutrements, and the like; that wretched Generation is unworthy of the name of <hi>Men,</hi> much more
<pb facs="tcp:112444:7"/>of <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) yet wil unthankfully cry out, What have we got by all theſe troubles? and what hath been done? ſurely this <hi>Iew</hi> ſhall riſe up in Judgement againſt ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Chriſtians; for he in his Epiſtle dedicatory ſayes, <hi>The whole world ſtands ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed at what the Parliament hath done;</hi> beſides, he cordially and openly ownes the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who as farre as I know, never did him, or his Nation any further good then to pray for them; <hi>(though we hope, and pray, that their favour may extend to realities, towards that people, to whom certainly God hath made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and great Promiſes, and ſhortly will give an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable performances:)</hi> but many among us, who enjoy peace under them, and many other bleſſings, (too many for an unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Generation) doe refuſe to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge them, doe curſe them whom God hath bleſſed, and even in their prayers to that God who cannot be deceived, or impoſed upon; doe vent themſelves againſt this preſent Government, in expreſſions ſo wilde and falſe, that ſuch Language would be accounted moſt unworthy, in our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe to any conſiderable perſon, much more then to the great God. I ſhall only adde this, ſc. Doe not think that I ayme by this Tranſlation to propagate, or commend
<pb facs="tcp:112444:8"/>
               <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> (which its no wonder if the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor doth ſo much favour, eſpecially in his thirtyeth Section) no, through Grace I have better learned the truth, as it is in Jeſus: but to give ſome diſcovery of what apprehenſions, and workings there are at this day in the hearts of the <hi>Iewes;</hi> and to remove our ſinfull hatred from off that people, whoſe are the Promiſes, and who are beloved for their Fathers ſakes; and who of <hi>Iewes,</hi> we ſhall heare to be, ere long, reall Chriſtians.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_quoted_authors">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112444:8"/>
            <head>The Authors of other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are quoted in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A.</head>
               <item>ABrahamus Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telius</item>
               <item>Agathias</item>
               <item>Auguſtinus</item>
               <item>Alexis Vanegas</item>
               <item>Alfonſus Cemedro</item>
               <item>Alonſus Auguſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</item>
               <item>Alonſus de Erzilla</item>
               <item>Alonſus Venerus</item>
               <item>Arias Montanus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B.</head>
               <item>Baronius</item>
               <item>Beroſus</item>
               <item>Boterus</item>
               <item>Bozius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C.</head>
               <item>Conſtantinus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D.</head>
               <item>Diodorus Siculus.</item>
               <item>Dion</item>
               <item>Duretus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E.</head>
               <item>Eſelius Geradus</item>
               <item>Euſebius Ceſarienſis.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F.</head>
               <item>Famianus Strada</item>
               <item>Franciſcus de Ribera</item>
               <item>Franciſcus lopez de</item>
               <item>Gomara.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G.</head>
               <item>Garcilaſſus dela Vega</item>
               <item>Genebrardus</item>
               <item>Goropius</item>
               <item>Guil. Poſtellus</item>
               <item>Guilielmus Blawius</item>
               <item>Guil. Schikardus.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112444:9"/>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>Henricus Alangre</item>
               <item>Hugo Grotius.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I.</head>
               <item>Jacobus Verus</item>
               <item>Joan. de caſtillanos</item>
               <item>Joan. de Bairos</item>
               <item>Joan. Roman</item>
               <item>Joan. de Laet</item>
               <item>Joan. Huarte</item>
               <item>Joſephus d' Acoſta</item>
               <item>Ioan. Linſchoten.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L.</head>
               <item>Leſcarbotus</item>
               <item>Lucanus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M.</head>
               <item>Manuel Sa.</item>
               <item>Marcilius Ficinus</item>
               <item>Marinus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N.</head>
               <item>Nicolaus Trigautius</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O.</head>
               <item>Origines</item>
               <item>Oroſius</item>
               <item>Oſorius Luſitanus.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P.</head>
               <item>Petrus de Cieza</item>
               <item>Plancius</item>
               <item>Petrus Simon</item>
               <item>Petrus Hernandes de</item>
               <item>Quiros</item>
               <item>Petrus Teixera</item>
               <item>Pineda</item>
               <item>Plato</item>
               <item>Plinius</item>
               <item>Pomarius</item>
               <item>Proclus</item>
               <item>Porphyrius</item>
               <item>Poſſevinus</item>
               <item>Plutarchus</item>
               <item>Picus Mirandulanus</item>
               <item>Ptolomaeus</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S.</head>
               <item>Semuel Bochardus</item>
               <item>Solinus</item>
               <item>Strabo</item>
               <item>Suetonius Tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T.</head>
               <item>Tacitus</item>
               <item>Thomas Malvenda</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>X.</head>
               <item>Xenophon.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Z.</head>
               <item>Zarate.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_Hebrew_books_and_authors">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112444:9"/>
            <head>The Hebrew Books, and Authors.</head>
            <list>
               <item>TAlmud Hieroſolymitanum</item>
               <item>Talmud Babylonicum</item>
               <item>Paraphraſis Chaldaica</item>
               <item>R. Simhon ben Johay</item>
               <item>Seder holam</item>
               <item>Rabot</item>
               <item>Ialkot</item>
               <item>Tanhuma</item>
               <item>Joſeph ben Gurion</item>
               <item>R. Sehadia Gaon</item>
               <item>R. Moſeh de Egypto</item>
               <item>R. Abraham Aben Ezra</item>
               <item>R. Selomoh Iarhi</item>
               <item>Eldad Danita</item>
               <item>R. David Kimhi</item>
               <item>Eldad Danita</item>
               <item>R. David Kimhi</item>
               <item>R. Benjamin Tudelenſis</item>
               <item>R. Moſeh Gerundenſis</item>
               <item>R. Abraham bar R. Hiya</item>
               <item>Don Shac Abarbanel</item>
               <item>R. Joſeph. Coen</item>
               <item>R. Abraham Friſol</item>
               <item>R. Mordechay Japhe</item>
               <item>R. Mordechay reato</item>
               <item>R. Hazarya a Adomi</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="relation">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:112444:10"/>
            <head>THE RELATION OF <hi>ANTONY MONTEZINVS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the <hi>18th.</hi> of the Month of <hi>Elul,</hi> the <hi>5404</hi> yeare from the Worlds creation, and according to common compute, in <hi>1644. Aaron Levi,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Antonius Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezinus</hi> came into this City <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> and related to the Sieur <hi>Menaſſih ben Iſrael,</hi> and other Cheiſetaines of the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall</hi> Nation, Inhabitants of the ſame City, theſe things which follow.</p>
            <p>That it was two years and an halfe, ſince that the going from the Port <hi>Honda</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> to the <hi>Papian</hi> juriſdiction, he conducted ſome Mules of a certain <hi>Indian,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Franciſcus Caſtellanus,</hi> into the Province of <hi>Qulty,</hi> and that there was one in company with him and other <hi>Indians,</hi> whoſe name was <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus,</hi> who was called by all <hi>Cazicus.</hi> That
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112444:10"/>it happened that as they went over the Mountaines <hi>Cordillerae,</hi> a great tempeſt aroſe, which threw the loaden Mules to the ground. The <hi>Indians</hi> being afflicted by the ſore tempeſt, every one began to count his loſſes; yet confeſſing that all that and more grievous puniſhments were but juſt, in regard of their many ſins. But <hi>Franciſcus</hi> bad them take it patiently, for that they ſhould ſhortly injoy reſt: The others anſwered, that they were unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of it, yea, that the notorius cruelty uſed by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> towards them, was ſent of God, becauſe they had ſo ill treated his holy people, who were of all others the moſt innocent. Now then, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to ſtay all night upon the top of the Mountaine. And <hi>Montezinus</hi> took out of a Box ſome Bread, and Cheeſe, and Junkets, and gave them to <hi>Franciſcus,</hi> upbraiding him, that he had ſpoken diſgracefully of the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> who an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that he had not told one halfe of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and calamities inflicted by a cruell, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane people; but they ſhould not goe unreven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, looking for help from an unknowne people.</p>
            <p>After this Conference, <hi>Montezinus</hi> went to <hi>Carthagena,</hi> a City of the <hi>Indians,</hi> where he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing examined, was put in priſon; and while he prayed to God, ſuch words fell from him; Bleſſed be the name of the Lord, that hath not made me an Idolater, a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> a <hi>Black-a-Moore,</hi> or an <hi>Indian;</hi> but as he named <hi>Indian,</hi> he was
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112444:11"/>angry with himſelf, and ſaid, The <hi>Hebrews</hi> are <hi>Indians;</hi> then he comming to himſelf againe, confeſſed that he doted, and added, Can the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> be <hi>Indians?</hi> which he alſo repeated a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and a third time; and he thought that it was not by chance that he had ſo much miſtaken him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>He thinking farther, of what he had heard from the <hi>Indian,</hi> and hoping that he ſhould finde out the whole truth; therefore as ſoone as he was let out of Priſon, he ſought out <hi>Franciſcus,</hi> beleeving that he would repeat to him again what he had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; he therefore being ſet at liberty, through Gods mercy, went to the Port <hi>Honda,</hi> and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his deſire, found him, who ſaid; He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred all that be had ſpoken, when he was upon the Mountaine; whom <hi>Montezinus</hi> asked, that he would take a Journey with him, offering him all courteſies, giving him three Peices of Eight, that he might buy himſelfe neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>Now when they were got out of the City, <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezinus</hi> confeſſed himſelfe to be an <hi>Hebrew,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and that the Lord was his Gods; and he told the <hi>Indian,</hi> that all other gods were but mockeries; the <hi>Indian</hi> being amazed, asked him the name of his Parents; who anſwered, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob;</hi> but ſaid he, have you no other Father? who anſwered, yes, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers name was <hi>Ludovicus Montezinus;</hi> but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112444:11"/>he not being yet ſatisfied, I am glad (ſaith he) to heare you tell this, for I was in doubt to beleeve you, while you ſeemed ignorant of your Parents: <hi>Montezinus</hi> ſwearing, that he ſpoke the truth, the <hi>Indian</hi> asked him, if he were not the Son of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> and thereupon began a long diſcourſe; who when he knew that he was ſo, he deſired him to proſecute what he had begun, and added, that he ſhould more fully explaine himſelfe, for that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly he had left things ſo doubtfull, that he did not ſeeme at all aſſured of any thing. After that both had ſate down together, and refreſhed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the <hi>Indian</hi> thus began: If you have minde to follow me your Leader, you ſhall know what ever you deſire to know, only let me tell you this, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the journy is, you muſt foot it, and you muſt eate nothing but parched <hi>Mayz,</hi> and you muſt omit nothing that I tell you; <hi>Montezinus</hi> anſwered, that he would doe all.</p>
            <p>The next day being Munday, <hi>Cazicus</hi> came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and bid him throw away what he had in his Knapſack, to put on ſhooes made of linnen pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thred, and to follow him, with his ſtaffe; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Montezinus</hi> leaving his Cloake, and his Sword, and other things which he had about him, they began the journey, the <hi>Indian</hi> carrying upon his back three meaſures of <hi>Mayz,</hi> two ropes, one of which was full of knots, to climbe up the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, with an booked ſork; the other was looſe,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112444:12"/>for to paſſe over Marſhes, and Rivers, with a little Axe, and ſhooes made of linnen pack-thread. They being thus accoutred, travelled the whole week, unto the Sabbath Day; on which day they teſting, the day after they went on, till Tueſday, on which day about eight a clock in the morning, they came to a River as bigge as <hi>Duerus;</hi> then the <hi>Indian</hi> ſaid, Here you ſhall ſee your Brethren, and making a ſign with the ſine linnen of <hi>Xylus,</hi> which they had about them inſtead of a Girdle; thereupon on the other ſide of the River they ſaw a great ſmoke, and immediatly after, ſuch another ſigne made as they had made before; a little after that, three men, with a woman, in a little Boat came to them, which being come near, the woman went aſhore, the reſt ſtaying in the Boat; who talking a good while with the <hi>Indian,</hi> in a Language which <hi>Montezinus</hi> underſtood not; ſhe returned to the Boat, and told to the three men what ſhe had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the <hi>Indian;</hi> who alwayes eying him, came preſently out of the Boat, and embraced <hi>Montezi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> the woman after their example doing the like; after which, one of them went back to the Boat, and when the <hi>Indian</hi> bowed down to the feet of the other two, and of the woman, they embraced him courteouſly, and talked a good while with him. After that, the <hi>Indian</hi> bid <hi>Montezinus</hi> to be of good courage, and not to look that they ſhould come a ſecond time to him, till he had ſully learned the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112444:12"/>things which were told him at the firſt time.</p>
            <p>Then thoſe two men comming on each ſide of <hi>Montezinus,</hi> they ſpoke in Hebrew, the fourth Verſe of <hi>Deut. 6. Semah Iſrael, adonai Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henu adonai chad;</hi> that is, <hi>Heare O Iſrael, the Lord our God is one God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then the <hi>Indian</hi> Interpreter being asked, how it was in <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> they ſpoke what followes to <hi>Montezinus,</hi> making a ſhort pauſe between every particular.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1 Our Fathers are</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob, <hi>and</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and they ſignified theſe foure by the three fingers lifted up; then they joyned</hi> Reuben, <hi>adding another finger to the former three.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2 We will beſtow ſeverall places on them who have a minde to live with us.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> Joſeph <hi>dwels in the midſt of the Sea, they making a ſigne by two fingers put to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and then parted them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4 They ſaid (ſpeaking faſt) ſhortly ſome of us will goe forth to ſee, and to tread under foot; at which word they winked, and ſtamped with their feet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5 One day we ſhall all of us talke toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they ſaying, Ba, ba, ba; and we ſhall come forth as iſſuing out of our mother the earth.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:112444:13"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>6 A certaine Meſſenger ſhall goe forth.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Franciſcus <hi>ſhall tell you ſomewhat more of theſe things, they making a ſigne with their finger, that much muſt not be ſpoken.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8 Suffer us that we may prepare our ſelves; and they turning their hands and faces every way, thus prayed to God, DO NOT STAY LONG.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9 Send twelve men, they making a ſign, that they would have men that had beards, and who are skilfull in writing.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Conference being ended, which laſted a whole day, the ſame men returned on Wedneſday, and Thurſday, and ſpake the ſame things againe, without adding a word; at laſt <hi>Montezinus</hi> being weary that they did not anſwer what be asked them, nor would ſuffer him to goe over the river, he caſt himſelfe into their Boat; but he being forced out againe, fell into the river, and was in danger to be drowned, for be could not ſwim; but being got out of the water, the reſt being angry, ſaid to him; at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt not to paſſe the River, nor to enquire after more then we tell you; which the <hi>Indian</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, the reſt declaring the ſame things both by ſignes, and words.</p>
            <p>You muſt obſerve, that all thoſe three dayes the Boat ſtayed not in the ſame place, but when thoſe four who came went away, other four came, who all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112444:13"/>as with one mouth, repeated all the fore-mentioned nine particulars, there came and went about three hundred.</p>
            <p>Thoſe men are ſomewhat ſcorched by the Sun, ſome of them weare their haire long, down to their knees, others of them ſhorter, and others of them much as we commonly cut it. They were comely of body, well accoutred, having ornaments on their feet, and leggs, and their heads were compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with a linnen cloath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Montezinus</hi> ſaith, that when he was about to be gone, on Thurſday evening, they ſhewed him very much courteſie, &amp; brought him whatever they thought fit for him in his journy, and they ſaid, that them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were well provided with all ſuch things, (ſc. meats, garments, flocks, and other things) which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in <hi>India</hi> call their owne.</p>
            <p>The ſame day, when they came to the place where they had reſted, the night before they came to the River, <hi>Montezinus</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Indian;</hi> You re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Francis,</hi> that my Brethren told me, that you ſhould tell me ſomething, therefore I entreat you, that you would not think much to relate it. The <hi>Indian</hi> anſwered, I will tell you what I know, only doe not trouble are, and you ſhall know the truth, as I have received it from my fore-fathers; but if you preſſe me too much, as you ſeeme to doe, you will make me tell you lyes; attend therefore I pray, to what I ſhall tell you.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:112444:14"/>
            <p>Thy Brethren are the Sons of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and brought thither by the providence of God, who for their ſake wrought many Miracles, which you will not beleeve, if I ſhould tell you what I have learned from my Fathers; we <hi>Indians</hi> made war upon them in that place, and uſed them more hardly then we now are by the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> then by the inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Magicians (whom we call <hi>Mohanes</hi>) we went armed to that place where you ſaw your Brethren, with an intent to deſtroy them; but not one of all thoſe who went thither, came back again; whereupon we raiſed a great Army, and ſet upon them, but with the ſame ſucceſſe, for againe none eſcaped; which hapned alſo the third time, ſo that <hi>India</hi> was almoſt bereft of all inhabitants, but old men, and women; the old men therefore, and the reſt who ſurvived, beleeving that the Magicians uſed falſe dealing, conſulted to deſtroy them all, and many of them being killed, thoſe who remained pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to diſcover ſomewhat that was not knowne; upon that they deſiſted from cruelty, and they decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch things as follow:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the God of thoſe Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>is the true God, that all that which is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven upon their ſtones is true; that about the end of the World they ſhall be Lords of the world; that ſome ſhall come who ſhall bring you much good, and after that they have enriched the earth with al good things,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112444:14"/>thoſe Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>going forth out of their Country, ſhall ſubdue the whole World to them, as it was ſubject to them formerly; you ſhall be happy if you make a League with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then five of the chief <hi>Indians</hi> (whom they call <hi>Cazici</hi> who were my Anceſtors, having underſtood the Propheſie of the Magicians, which they had learned of the Wiſe men of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> went thither, and after much entreaty, obtained their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, having firſt made knowne their minde to that woman, whom you ſaw to be for an Interpreter, (for your Brethren will have no commerce with our <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi>) and whoſoever of ours doth enter the Country of your Brethren, they preſently kill him; and none of your Brethren doe paſſe into our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. Now by the help of that woman we made this agreement with them.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1 That our fifth</hi> Cazici <hi>ſhould come to them, and that alone at every ſeventy months end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2 That he to whom ſecrets ſhould be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, ſhould be above the age of three hundred Moons, or months.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3 And that ſuch things ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to none in any place where people are, but only in a Deſart, and in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the</hi> Cazici; <hi>and ſo (ſaid the</hi> Indian) <hi>we keep that ſecret among our ſelves, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112444:15"/>that we promiſe our ſelves great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from them, for the good offices which we have done to our Brethren, it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for us to viſite them, unleſſe at the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty months end: Or if there happens any thing new, and this fell out but thrice in my time; Firſt, when the</hi> Spaniards <hi>came into this Land; alſo, when Ships came into the Southern Sea; and thirdly, when you came, whom they long wiſhed for, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. They did much rejoyce for thoſe three new things, becauſe that they ſaid, the Propheſies were fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Montezinus</hi> alſo ſaid, that three other <hi>Cazici</hi> were ſent to him by <hi>Franciſcus,</hi> to <hi>Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> yet not telling their names; till he had ſaid, you may ſpeak to them freely, they are my fellowes in my Function, of whom I have told you, the fifth could not come for age, but thoſe three did hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily embrace him; and <hi>Montezinus</hi> being asked, of what Nation he was, he anſwered, an <hi>Hebrew,</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and that God was his God, &amp;c. which when they had heard, they embraced him againe, and ſaid: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a time you ſhall ſee us; and ſhall not know us; we are all your Brethren, by Gods ſingular favour; and again, they both of them hidding farewell, departed, every one ſaying, I goe about my buſineſſe; therefore none-but <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſcus</hi> being left, who ſaluting <hi>Montezinus</hi> as a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112444:15"/>Brother, then bade him farewell, ſaying, farewell my Brother, <hi>I</hi> have other things to doe, and I goe to viſite thy Brethren, with other <hi>Hebrew</hi> Cazici<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As for the Country, be ſecure, for we rule all the <hi>Indians;</hi> after we have finiſhed a buſineſſe which we have with the wicked <hi>Spaniards,</hi> we will bring you out of your bondage, by Gods help; not doubting, but he who cannot lye, will help us, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Word; endeavour you in the meane while that thoſe men may come.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>The HOPE of ISRAEL.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT 1.</head>
               <p>IT is hard to ſay what is certaine among the ſo many, &amp; ſo uncertain opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the originall of the <hi>Indians</hi> of the new world. If you aske, what is my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion upon the relation of <hi>Montezinus,</hi> I muſt ſay, it is ſcarce poſſible to know it by any Art, ſince there is no demonſtration, which can manifeſt the truth of it; much leſſe can you gather it from Divine, or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Writings; for the Scriptures doe not tell what people firſt inhabited thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; neither was there mention of them by any, til <hi>Chriſtop. Columbus, Americus Veſpucius, Ferdinandus Cortez,</hi> the Marqueſſe <hi>Del Valle,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:112444:16"/>and <hi>Franciſcus Pizarrus</hi> went thither; and though hitherto I have been of this minde, that I would ſpeake only of ſolid, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible things, (as thoſe things are which concerne our Law) and the obſcurity of the matter, making me doubt, whether it would be worth a while for me to attempt it; yet at laſt I was content to be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it, not that I look to get credit by it, but that my friends, and all who ſeeke for truth, that have put me upon this work, may ſee how very deſirous I am to pleaſe them.</p>
               <p>I ſhall ſpeak ſomewhat in this Diſcourſe, of the divers opinions which have been, and ſhall declare in what Countries it is thought the ten Tribes are; and I ſhall cloſe, after that I have brought them into their owne Country, which I ſhall prove by good reaſons, following the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the holy Prophets, who I beleeve cannot be expounded otherwiſe, whatever ſome thinke; yet I intend not to diſpute theſe things, but according to my cuſtom, ſhall lay downe fairly, and faithfully, the opinions of the <hi>Iewes</hi> only.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:112444:16"/>
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p>YOu muſt know therefore, that <hi>Alexis Vanegas</hi> ſaith, that the firſt Colonies of the <hi>Weſt-Indies</hi> were of the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> who firſt of all inhabited <hi>New-Spaine,</hi> and as they encreaſed, ſpread to the Iland <hi>Cuba;</hi> from thence to the continent of <hi>America;</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that towards <hi>Panama, New-Spaine,</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Peru.</hi> And he grounds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on that reaſon, that as the <hi>Cartha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginians</hi> (who of old did moſt uſe the Seas) ſo thoſe of <hi>Peru,</hi> and the Inhabitants of <hi>New-Spaine,</hi> did make uſe of pictures inſtead of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>But this opinion doth not ſatisfie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they anciently were white men, bearded, and civill in converſe; but contrarily thoſe of <hi>Parama, St. Martha,</hi> and of the iſles of <hi>Cuba,</hi> and <hi>Barlovent,</hi> went naked. Farther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, who can thinke that the language which; he ſaith, they firſt ſpoke, ſhould be ſo ſoone changed, that it ſhould be wholly another: and there is no agreement between the one and the other. The learned <hi>Arias Montanus</hi> thinkes, that the <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>New Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> are the off-ſpring of <hi>Ophir</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Jokton,</hi> the nephew of <hi>Heber.</hi> And he backs his opinion, by the name <hi>Ophir,</hi> which by tranſpoſition of letters, is the ſame with <hi>Peru;</hi> and he adds, that the name <hi>Parvaim</hi> in the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112444:17"/>number, doth ſignifie the <hi>Iſtimus</hi> between <hi>New-Spaine</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> which firſt was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Ophir,</hi> then <hi>Peru;</hi> and that theſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries are that <hi>Peru,</hi> from whence King <hi>Solomon</hi> brought gold, precious ſtones, &amp;c. as in 1 <hi>Kin. chap.</hi> 9.6.10. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 9.21. This opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſeemes more probable than the other, and may be backed by another name of the River <hi>Liru,</hi> which according to <hi>Gomoras,</hi> lies in the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> degree from the Equinoctiall line, from <hi>Panama</hi> 222. miles; as alſo by the name of the Province <hi>Jucatan,</hi> which may be derived from <hi>Joktan</hi> the father of <hi>Ophir.</hi> But beſides that this notation is ſomewhat farre fetcht, it croſſes what <hi>Joſephus Acoſta</hi> affirmes in 1. <hi>Hiſtor.</hi> of <hi>Jud. c.</hi> 13. who ſayth, that the name <hi>Peru</hi> was unknown to the <hi>Indians</hi> themſelves before thoſe <hi>Spaniards</hi> gave that name. Add to this what <hi>Garcillaſſo de la Vega</hi> in the firſt part of his Commentary on <hi>Peru, c.</hi> 4 ſaith, that when a certaine <hi>Spanyard, Baſco Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nez de Balboa,</hi> lived in that country, and asked a Fiſherman, what was the name of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, he anſwered <hi>Beru;</hi> (which was the Fiſhermans owne name, he thinking that was the queſtion) and he farther ſaid, that the name of the River where he fiſhed, was called <hi>Pelu.</hi> Hence you may ſee, that <hi>Peru</hi> is made of both thoſe words; which alſo many <hi>Spanyards</hi> beſides him, we have mentioned, doe teſtifie.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112444:17"/>Beſides, who can thinke that <hi>Solomon</hi> neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> a place ſo rich, and aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with all things, ſhould ſend a Fleet ſo farre off as to the <hi>Weſt-Indies.</hi> Alſo we read in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 9. that <hi>Solomon</hi> made ſhips in <hi>Ezion-Geber</hi> on the ſhoare of the red Sea, which alſo <hi>Jehoſophat</hi> did, with <hi>Ahaziah,</hi> as <hi>Ezra</hi> ſaith, in 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. and it is certaine that thoſe of thoſe countries went that ordinary way to <hi>India.</hi> And it will not follow, that becauſe the holy Scripture ſometimes ſaith, that they went to <hi>Tarſis,</hi> and ſometimes that they went to <hi>Ophir,</hi> that therefore both thoſe places are the ſame; ſince that <hi>Tarſis</hi> is not, as ſome thinke <hi>Carthage,</hi> or <hi>Tunes</hi> in <hi>Africa;</hi> for that the navy of <hi>Solomon</hi> did not ſet ſayle from <hi>Joppa,</hi> a Port of the mediterranean, but from <hi>Ezion-Geber,</hi> a Port of the red Sea, from whence they could not ſaile to <hi>Carthage,</hi> but to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies.</hi> The anſwer of <hi>Iſaac Abarbanel</hi> to that argument, cannot be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, who ſaith, that an arme of <hi>Nilus</hi> did run into the red Sea, and another arme ran into the Mediterranean, by <hi>Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Aegypt;</hi> ſince it was never heard, that ſhips of great bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, did ſwim in thoſe rivers; and would not he then have built his Navy in the Port of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria?</hi> It is more true that <hi>Tarſis</hi> is the Ocean, or <hi>Indian</hi> Sea; and becauſe they came into the Ocean, after that they had ſailed over
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112444:18"/>the red Sea, which is but narrow, therefore the Scripture ſaith, <hi>They Sailed to Tarſis. Rabbi Jonathan ben Vziel</hi> followes this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, who in his Paraphraſe, for <hi>Tarſis,</hi> puts (the Sea.) The ſame ſaith <hi>Franciſcus de Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bera,</hi> in his Comment on <hi>Jonah,</hi> and alſo <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus Joſephus Coen,</hi> in his <hi>Chronology;</hi> who aſcribe the word <hi>Tarſis,</hi> to the <hi>Indian</hi> Sea; becauſe that <hi>Ophir</hi> is the ſame country, which of old is called <hi>The Golden Cherſoneſus;</hi> and by <hi>Joſephus, The golden Land;</hi> and at this day <hi>Malacca;</hi> from whence they brought Ivory, for the great number of Elephants which are there; none of which are in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> And <hi>Solomons</hi> Navy ſtayd in thoſe Ports of <hi>India,</hi> 3. yeares, becauſe they traded with the Inhabitants I know that learned <hi>Grotius,</hi> and famous <hi>de Lact</hi> thinke differently; as alſo thoſe quoted by them; but I ſhall not inſiſt in confuting their opinions becauſe I ſtudy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. I doe like of, in part, the opinion of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> who dwell in the <hi>Indies,</hi> who by common conſent doe affirme that the <hi>Indians</hi> come of the 10. Tribes. And truly they are not altogether miſtaken, becauſe in my opinion, <hi>they were the firſt planters of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;</hi> as alſo other people of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> came by that Streight which is betweene <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> and the Kingdome of <hi>Anian.</hi> But that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, according to our <hi>Montezinus,</hi> made warre
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112444:18"/>upon thoſe Inhabitants the <hi>Iſralites,</hi> whom they forced up unto the mountaines, and the in-land countries, as formerly the <hi>Brittaines</hi> were driven by the <hi>Saxons</hi> into <hi>Wales.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p>THe firſt ground of that opinion is taken from 2 <hi>Eſdraſ.</hi> 13. <hi>v.</hi> 40. &amp;c, (which we quote as ancient, though it be Apocryphall) where it's ſaid, that the 10. Tribes which <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manaſter</hi> carried captive in the raigne of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeas,</hi> beyond <hi>Euphrates,</hi> determined to goe into countries farre remote, in which none dwelt, whereby they might the better obſerve their law. And as they paſſed over ſome bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Euphrates,</hi> God wrought miracles, ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the courſe of the Flood, till they had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over; and that country is called <hi>Arſareth.</hi> From whence we may gather, that the 10. Tribes, went to <hi>New-Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Peru,</hi> and poſſeſſed thoſe 2 Kingdomes, till then without Inhabitants. <hi>Genebrardus,</hi> quoting <hi>Eſdras</hi> concerning that wandring of the 10. Tribes, ſaith, that <hi>Arſareth</hi> is <hi>Tartaria</hi> the greater, and from thence they went to <hi>Greenland;</hi> becauſe that <hi>America</hi> is lately found compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with it, and ſo it is to be on that ſide farther from Sea, than it is upon other ſides, being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt an Iland; and they might paſſe from <hi>Greenland,</hi> by the Streight of <hi>Davis</hi> into the country <hi>Labrador,</hi> which is now called <hi>India,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:112444:19"/>being 50. miles diſtant from thence, as <hi>Gome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> ſaith in his Hiſtory: The ſame journying of the 10 Tribes into <hi>India,</hi> is confirmed by that which <hi>P. Malvenda</hi> reports. That <hi>Arſareth</hi> is that Promontry which is neare to <hi>Scythia,</hi> or <hi>Tartary,</hi> neare the Sea, called by <hi>Pliny, Tabis,</hi> where <hi>America</hi> is parted from the country of <hi>Anian</hi> by a narrow Sea; which alſo on that ſide parts <hi>China,</hi> or <hi>Tartary</hi> from <hi>America;</hi> ſo that there might be an eaſie paſſage for the 10. Tribes through <hi>Arſareth,</hi> or <hi>Tartary</hi> into the Kingdomes of <hi>Anian,</hi> and <hi>Quivira;</hi> which in time might plant the new world, and firme land; which in bigneſſe equals <hi>Europe, Aſia,</hi> and <hi>Africa</hi> put together; <hi>Alonſus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtinianus</hi> counting from the ſhoare of the north Sea, from the country of <hi>Labrador</hi> 3928. miles, and from <hi>Sur</hi> 3000. miles; but <hi>Goma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> counts from <hi>India</hi> by the South, and <hi>Sur</hi> 9300. miles; which ſpace is big enough for the 10. Tribes, that they may there ſpread in places hitherto unknowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <p>HE ſtrengthens this opinion, that in the iſle S. <hi>Michael,</hi> which belongs to the <hi>Azo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> found Sepulchres under ground, with very ancient Hebrew letters, which <hi>Genebrardus</hi> hath Printed, <hi>in lib.</hi> 1. <hi>chro. p.</hi> 159. From whence we gather, that in that inſcription there is a miſtake of the Letter (T),
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:112444:19"/>ſo that the ſenſe of it is, <hi>How perfect is God. Sehalbin is dead. Know God.</hi> Unleſs you will have them to be proper Names, and to ſignifie him that is dead, and his Father, in which ſenſe for (M) you muſt read (B), and then the ſenſe will be, <hi>Meetabel, ſeal, the Son of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadel;</hi> ſuch names ending in (el) are common in Scripture, as <hi>Raphael, Immanuel,</hi> and the like. Let it ſuffice him who is pleaſed with neither of thoſe conjectures, that Hebrew Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were found there. And though that Iland is remote from the Weſt-Indies, yet it might be by accident that they might put in thither.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 5.</head>
               <p>THat ſeems to be to the purpeſe which <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cillaſſe de la Voga</hi> ſaith in his Comment on <hi>Peru, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>That in Tiahuanacis a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of Collai, among other Antiquities, this is worthy of memory, (being ſcituated at the Lake which the Spaniards call Chutuytu) That among the great buildings which are there, one was to be ſeen of a very great pile, which hath a Court</hi> 15 <hi>fathoms broad; a wall that compaſſeth it,</hi> 2 <hi>furlongs high; on one ſide of the Court is a Chamber</hi> 45 <hi>foot long, and</hi> 22 <hi>broad; and the Court, the Wall, the Pavement, the Chamber, the Roofe of it, the entrance, the poſts of the</hi> 2 <hi>gates of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and of the entrance, are made onely of one ſtone; the three ſides of the Wall are an ell
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112444:20"/>thick; the Indians ſay, that that Houſe is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to the Maker of the World.</hi> I conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture that building to be a Synagogue, built by the Iſraelites; for the Authors who writ about the <hi>Indies,</hi> tell us, that the <hi>Indians</hi> never uſe iron, or iron weapons. Alſo the <hi>Indians</hi> were Idolaters, and therefore it could not be that they ſhould build an houſe to God. <hi>P. Acoſta in lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Ind. hiſtor. c.</hi> 14. mentions ſuch buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings as are in that place; and he reports that he meſured a ſtone which was 38 foot long, 18 foot broad, and 6 foot thick. <hi>Petrus Cie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> in his firſt part of his Chonicles of <hi>Peru, c.</hi> 87. relates, That in the City <hi>Guamanga,</hi> which is ſituated by the river <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>inaque,</hi> there is a vaſt building, which becauſe then it ſeemed almoſt ruined by time, it therefore had laſted many yeares. He asking the neighbouring <hi>Indians.</hi> Who built that great Pile? he learnt, that it was made by a people (who were bearded, and white as the <hi>Spaniards</hi>) who came thither a long time before (and ſtaid ſome time after) the <hi>Indians</hi> raigned there; and the <hi>Indians</hi> ſaid, that they had received it from their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by Tradition. The ſame <hi>Cieza cap.</hi> 10 5. of the Antiquity of <hi>Tiguanac,</hi> ſaith, that what the <hi>Indians</hi> boa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t to be very ancient, can by no meanes be compared with that Ancient buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and other things. From all which you may well gather, that the firſt inhabitants of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:112444:20"/>that place were the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of the 10 Tribes becauſe they were white, and bearded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 6.</head>
               <p>TO this opinion adde an argument taken from what Logicians call <hi>à ſimili;</hi> for he that will compare the Lawes and Cuſtomes of the <hi>Indians</hi> and <hi>Hebrews</hi> together, ſhall finde them agree in many things; whence you may eaſily gather, That the <hi>Indians</hi> borrowed thoſe of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> (who lived among them) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or after they went to the unknown moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. The <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>Jucatan,</hi> and the <hi>Acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zainitenſes</hi> do circumeiſe themſelves. The <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tones</hi> of <hi>New Spain,</hi> and <hi>Mexicans</hi> (as <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Gomaza</hi> in the generall hiſtory of the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi> teſtifie) rend their garments, if their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen any ſudden misfortune, or the death of any. <hi>Gregorius Garcias in Monarchia Ingaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> an Iſle of <hi>Peru,</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Guainacapacus</hi> hearing that his ſon <hi>Atagualpa</hi> ſled for feare of the army of his enemy, he rent his garments. The <hi>Mexicans,</hi> and <hi>Totones,</hi> or the <hi>Totonaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenſes</hi> kept continually fire upon their altars, as God commands in <hi>Leviticus.</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Peru</hi> do the ſame, in their Temples dedicated to the Sun. The <hi>Nicaraguazenſes</hi> do forbid their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men who were lately brought a bed, to enter their Temples, till they are purified. The Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of <hi>Hiſpaniola</hi> think thoſe do ſin, who lye with a woman a little after her child-birth.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112444:21"/>And the <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>new Spain</hi> do ſeverely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Sodomie. Many of the <hi>Indians</hi> do bury their dead on the Mountains; which alſo is the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> cuſtome, and <hi>Garcias</hi> ſaith, the name <hi>Chanan</hi> to found in thoſe countries. You may wonder at this, that the <hi>Indians</hi> doe every 50. yeares celebrate a Jubily, with great pomp, in <hi>Mexico,</hi> the Metropolis of the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. Alſo that on the Sabbath-day all are bound to be preſent in the Temple, to perform their Sacrifices, and Ceremonies. They alſo were divorced from their wives, if they were not honeſt. The <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>Pern, New-Spain,</hi> and <hi>Guatemala</hi> did marry the widdowes of their dead brethren. May not you judge from theſe things, that the <hi>Jewes</hi> lived in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> learned ſuch things of them? Add alſo to what hath been ſaid, that the knowledge which the <hi>Indians</hi> had, of the creation of the world, and of the univerſall Flood, they borrowed from the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <p>THe 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ground of this opinion is, that the <hi>Indians</hi> are of a brown colour, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out beards; but in the new world, white, and bearded men were found, who had never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> and whom you cannot affirme to be any other than <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> becauſe alſo as they could never be overcome, ſo they ſhall never be fully known: as appears
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112444:21"/>by what followes. <hi>Petrus Simon a Franciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> in his Hiſtory of finding out the firme land, ſaith, that in the raigne of <hi>Charles</hi> the 5. he commanded one called <hi>Philippus de Vire</hi> thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to diſcover, and plant thoſe countries; that he found them unknown toward the north of <hi>America</hi> about 5. degrees, in the Province of <hi>Omeguas,</hi> which is neare the Province of <hi>Venezuela,</hi> and now is called <hi>Garracas.</hi> And he having learned of their neighbours, the greatneſſe of that people both in wealth, and in war, he determined to war upon them. Who when they had marched a good way, at laſt found a rich city, full of people, and faire buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; and not farre off 2 husbandmen tilling the ground; whom they would have made priſoners, that they might be their interpreters. But when they ſaw themſelves ſet on, they fled apace towards the city; but <hi>Philippus d' Vire</hi> and his Soldiers followed them hard on horſeback, and had almoſt taken them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the husbandmen ſtood ſtill, and with their Speares wounded <hi>Philip</hi> in the breaſt, piercing through his Breſt-plate made of wooll to keepe off arrowes. He wondering at the dexterity of that people, judged it a wiſer courſe, not to make war upon that Province, and people ſo expert in war, and who dared to reſiſt armed men. Therefore he retreated with his Company. And to this day none goe to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112444:22"/>that people, neither is it known which way to go to them. It is probable that they are <hi>Iſraelites</hi> whom God preſerves in that place againſt the day of redemption. <hi>Alonſus de Erzilla</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the ſame thing, in 2. part. <hi>ſua Araucaniae, Cant.</hi> 27. where deſcribing thoſe places, he thus ſpeakes in Spaniſh,
<q>
                     <l>Some Countries there, ſo populous are ſeen,</l>
                     <l>As one continued City; which have been</l>
                     <l>Never as yet, diſcoved; but unknown</l>
                     <l>To other Nations; have lyen hid alone;</l>
                     <l>Not found by forraine ſword, nor forrain trade</l>
                     <l>Doe either ſeeke, nor ſuffer to be made<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>But unacquainted live, till God ſhall pleaſe</l>
                     <l>To manifeſt his ſecrets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhew us theſe.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IOanues Caſtilianus Vicarius</hi> living in the City <hi>Pampelona</hi> of <hi>Nova Granada</hi> in <hi>Peru,</hi> ſaith, that when <hi>Gonzalus Piſarrus</hi> had revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from his people, he ſent ſome to ſearch out new countries of the <hi>Indians</hi> who lived eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, whoſe number could never be knowne, becauſe that (as ſome ſay) their country is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 2000 miles in length, if you compute from the head of the river <hi>Maragnon,</hi> which runnes neare <hi>Andes</hi> of <hi>Guſco,</hi> unto the place where it runs into the Sea, where therefore the River began to be navigable, <hi>Petrus d' Orſua</hi> being a Captaine, went by water, and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Soldiers with him, in Veſſels called Canows; which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112444:22"/>when they were too ſmall for the ſorce of the ſtreame, he built Brigandines, on the bank of the River <hi>Guariaga,</hi> which waſhing the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince <hi>Chachapoyas,</hi> runs into <hi>Maragnon.</hi> He was ſcarce gone aboord his Brigandines, when one of his owne Soldiers named <hi>Aquirre,</hi> a ſtout man, killed him, who by common conſent ſucceeded the ſlaine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> When they had gone a little way, they found a plain without a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, where many houſes ſtood on each ſide of the bank of <hi>Maragnon,</hi> being built by the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians.</hi> They ſtill went on for 48 houres toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſaw nothing but tall, and white hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which they feared to goe into, becauſe the Inhabitants were numerous, and becauſe they heard the noiſe of Hammers; for which cauſe they thought the Inhabitants to be Goldſmiths. They went on ſtill, and now ſailed in the north Sea, but alwayes neere to the ſhoar of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Margarita,</hi> where <hi>Aquirre</hi> was catcht by the Inhabitants and hanged; for they heard that he had killed his Captain <hi>Petrus de Orſua.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CAſpar Bergarenſis</hi> (whom I have oft ſpoke with) went from the City <hi>Loxa,</hi> which is in the Province of <hi>Quiti</hi> in <hi>Peru,</hi> and accompanied the Colonell <hi>Don Diego Vaca de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Vega</hi> going to ſeek a new Country.</p>
               <p>In the yeare 1622 they came to the Province <hi>Jarguaſongo,</hi> which had been diſcovered by
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112444:23"/>Captain <hi>Salines;</hi> and they paſſed the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines <hi>Cordillerae,</hi> where the River <hi>Maragnon</hi> is not above a ſtones caſt over. In the Province of the <hi>Iude Mainenſes</hi> they built a City, whoſe name was <hi>S. Franciſcus de Borja,</hi> at <hi>Eſquila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.</hi> In his company were an 100 <hi>Spaniards</hi> in Canows. Having conquered thoſe <hi>Indians,</hi> and compelling them to ſweare fealty to the King of <hi>Spaine;</hi> the Collonel being inſtructed by the <hi>Mainenſes,</hi> went to other places, after he had put a Garriſon into his new City. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſayled fifty leagues in the River (he found ſome Cottages of the <hi>Indians</hi> which there hid themſelves) by favour of many Rivers which there run into <hi>Maragnon.</hi> When they had ſailed into the River <hi>Guariaga,</hi> where <hi>Petrus de Orſua</hi> had built his Brigaudines, and was killed by <hi>Aquerra;</hi> they asked the <hi>Indians</hi> whom they had taken (who were called <hi>Gua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaga,</hi> from the Rivers name) what people doe live on the Rivers ſide? they told the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, that 5 dayes journey off, there live men of tall ſtature, comely in preſence, and have as great beards as the <hi>Spanyards</hi> have, valiant, and warlick, who are not skilled in Canowes, though the reſt of the <hi>Indians</hi> uſe no other; he preſently returned the ſame way he came.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:112444:23"/>
               <head>SECT. 10.</head>
               <p>IN Fardambuc about 40 years ſince, 8 Tabaiares had a mind to look out new Countries, and to ſee whether the Land that was beyond, and unknown, were inhabited. They having ſpent 4 moneths in travelling Weſtward, they came to mountains, to whoſe top they got with difficulty, and found a plain which a pleaſant river did compaſs, by whoſe bank ſide dwelt a people who loved commerce, they were white, and bearded; and this 5 of the Tabaires (for 3 periſhed by the way, and only 5 returned) told to the Braſilians after 9 moneths.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 11.</head>
               <p>IN our time, under King Philip the Third, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Ferdinandes de Queiros being returned out of India (where he had ſpent moſt of his life) to Rome, he ſhewed a Table of Lands yet undiſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. From thence he went to Madrid, and 5 ſhips were given him by che Governour of Panama (to whom he was ſent) to perfect his deſigne. He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan his journey, and was ſcarcely entred the South Sea, but he found land, which he called, The Iſle of Solomon, and Hieruſalem, for reaſons which he told me. He in his courſe of ſayling alwayes kept cloſe to the ſhoare of thoſe Iſlands; he ſaw thoſe Iſlanders of a browne colour, and took many; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers dwelt in greater Iſlands, and more fruitful; theſe were white, and wore long garments of ſilk; and the Pilot being bid to bring his Ship neere the ſhoare, he ſplit his Ship upon a Rock, and the Iſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders running greedily to the ſight) which being ſunke, the Captaine went thence, looking for the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112444:24"/>firme land, which he found to be forty degrees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond; and he went 300 miles neere the ſhoare And when he perceived the Countrey to be inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, by the ſmoak which he ſaw, and would put into a Port on the ſide of the River, there ran to him many white men, of yellow haire, tall like Giants, richly cloathed, and of long beards. But one of the Veſſels being wracked in the Havens mouth, he was forced to put out to Sea; whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Iſlanders ſent 2 Chaloffi of a brown colour, (as the inhabitants were of the firſt Iſland) with ſheep, and other proviſions, and fruits, but deſiring, and threatning them, if they did not depart: The Captaine brought thoſe Coloffi into Spaine, from whom the Spaniards could learne nothing but by ſignes; and in ſtead of anſwers, (when they were asked) would ſhew their beards, as if ſuch thoſe were, who were their Lords, and had ſent them, and if they were asked about Religion, they would hold up their fingers to heaven, implying, that they worſhipped but one God. A little while after, they died in Spain. The Captaine returned to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nama, having left his 2 Ships which were wrack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and when the Governour ſued him, by meanes. of the Senators, who are over the Indian affaires, he was diſmiſſed, and returned with his Ships into Spaine, where he abode 2 years before his matters were diſpatched. But the King created him Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of the Countries found out by him, and commanded to give him a good Army, wherewith to compaſſe his deſignes. But he ſcarce got to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nama, when he died, not without ſuſpition of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poiſoned by the Governour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:112444:24"/>
               <head>SECT: XII.</head>
               <p>THat which I am about to tell, ſhall ſerve for a proof of that which I ſaid of the Weſt-Indians. A Dutch mariner told me, that not long ſince he was with his ſhip in <hi>Ameri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> ſeven degrees towards the North between <hi>Maragnon,</hi> and great <hi>Para,</hi> and he put into an harbor in a pleaſant river, where he found ſome Indians who underſtood Spaniſh, of whom he bought Meats, and Dy-wood; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had ſtayed there ſix months, he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood that that River extended eighteen leagues towards the <hi>Carybes Indians,</hi> as far as the ſhip could go; and that the River is divided there into three branches, and they ſayling two months on the left hand, there met them white men, and bearded, well bred, well clothed, and abounding with gold and ſilver; they dwelt in Cities en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed with wals, and full of people; and that ſome Indians of <hi>Oronoch</hi> went thither, and brought home much gold, ſilver, and many precious ſtones. Which he having underſtood, ſent thither ſome Sea-men; but the Indian died by the way, who was their guide, and ſo they did not proceed, but ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there two months, and trucked with the Indians who were ſixty leagues from Sea. That Province is called <hi>Jisbia,</hi> and is ſubject
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112444:25"/>to <hi>Zealand;</hi> they have no commerce with the Spaniards, and the Inhabitants travell ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely every way. I heard that ſtory by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from that Dutch maſter of the ſhip; whence ſome of us gueſſing them to be Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, had purpoſed to ſend him again to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire more fully. But he dyed ſuddenly the laſt yeer, whence it ſeems that God doth not permit that thoſe purpoſes ſhould take any effect till the end of days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XIII.</head>
               <p>YEt I give more credit to our <hi>Monterinus,</hi> being a Portingal, and a Jew of our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; born in a City of <hi>Portingal,</hi> called <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleur,</hi> of honeſt and known parents, a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fourty yeers old, honeſt, and not ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious. He went to the Indies, where he was put into the Inquiſition as the ſucceſſor of many who were born in <hi>Portingal,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from them whom the King of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal <hi>Don Manuel</hi> forced to turn Chriſtians: (<hi>O wicked, and unjuſt action,</hi> ſaith <hi>Oſorius;</hi> and a little after, <hi>This was done neither according to Law, nor Religion,</hi>) and yet to this day they privately keep their Religion, which they had changed, being forced thereto. He being freed from the Inquiſition, very diligently ought out theſe things, and oft ſpoke with
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112444:25"/>thoſe men; and then was not quiet till he came hither, and had told us that good news. He endured much in that journey, and was driven to great want, ſo that no houſe would give him food, or give him money for his work. I my ſelf was well acquainted with him for ſix months together that he lived here; and ſometimes I made him take an oath in the preſence of honeſt men, that what he had told, was true. Then he went to <hi>Farnambuc,</hi> where two yeers after he died, taking the ſame oath at his death. Which if it be ſo, why ſhould not I beleeve a man that was vertuous, and having all that which men call gain. And who knows but that ſhortly the truth of that prognoſtick may appear, which our <hi>Monterinus</hi> learned from the <hi>Mohanes;</hi> anſwerable to that which <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobus Verus</hi> an Aſtrologer of <hi>Prague</hi> writ after the apparition of the Comet in <hi>Ann.</hi> 1618. and dedicated to his Highneſs the Prince <hi>Palatine,</hi> where he thus diſcourſeth: The Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met going towards the South, doth intimate that the Cities and Provinces which God doth threaten, are thoſe of the Weſt-Indies, which ſhall revolt from the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> who will finde that loſs greater then he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined, not that the <hi>Indians</hi> rebell againſt him of themſelves, but that they are provoked
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112444:26"/>to it being ſtirred up by others. Neither did the Comet only foretell that, but the eclipſe of the Sun, which was in that Countrey the yeer before. Thus far the Aſtrologer. Our ancient Rabbins ſay, though we do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the Aſtrologers in all things, yet we do not wholly reject them, who ſometimes tell truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XIIII.</head>
               <p>THus far of the Weſt-Indies; of which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> may be underſtood (becauſe it lyes in the midſt of the Sea, and alſo hath many Iſlands) in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.9. <hi>The iſles ſhall wait for me, and the ſhips of Tarſhiſh firſt, to bring their ſons from far, their ſilver and their gold with them.</hi> Jer. 31.10. <hi>Hear the word of the Lord O ye nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and declare it in the iſles afar off, and ſay, He that ſcattered Iſrael will gather him.</hi> Pſal. 97.1. <hi>The Lord reigneth, let the earth rejoyce, and the multitude of iſles be glad.</hi> Where part of the ten Tribes do dwell unknown to this day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XV.</head>
               <p>YOu muſt know, that all the ten Tribes were not carried away at the ſame time. <hi>Pul</hi> the King of Aſſyria (as I ſhew in the 2d: part of my Reconciler) conquered, and carried away the Tribes of <hi>Reuben, Gad,</hi> and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112444:26"/>half <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> in the reign of <hi>Peka,</hi> as you may ſee in 1 <hi>Chron:</hi> 5.26. and <hi>Joſephus in li.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>Tiglah-pileſer</hi> 8. yeers after took <hi>Ijon, Abel-beth-maachah, Hazor, Gilead, Galilee,</hi> all the land of <hi>Naphtali,</hi> and he carried away all the captives into Aſſyria, in 2 <hi>King.</hi> 15.29. At laſt <hi>Shalmaneſer</hi> king of Aſſyria, nine yeers after, in the reign of <hi>Hoſhea</hi> the ſon of <hi>Elah,</hi> beſieged Samaria three yeers; which being taken, he carried away <hi>Hoſhea,</hi> with the reſt of the Tribes, in 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.6. Of thoſe three times the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.1. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the firſt captivity was gentle, if you compare it with the laſt, which was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, and unſufferable, when the kingdom, and Monarchy of Iſrael ceaſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XVI.</head>
               <p>THe ten Tribes being conquered at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times, we muſt think they were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into ſeverall places. As we beleeve they went to the Weſt-Indies by the ſtrait of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, ſo we think that out of Tartary they went to China, by that famous wall in the confines of both. Our argument to prove it, is taken from the authority of two Jeſuites, who erected their Colledges in thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys. <hi>Nicolaus Trigantius</hi> a Dutch-man in his diſcourſe of the Chriſtian expedition under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112444:27"/>by the Jeſuites to Sina, ſaith, We finde that in former time the Jews came into theſe kingdoms. And when that ſociety had for ſome yeers ſeated it ſelf in the Court of the <hi>Pequinenſes,</hi> a certain Jew came to <hi>P. Matthaeus Riccius;</hi> he was born in <hi>Chamfamfu</hi> the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis of the Province <hi>Honan,</hi> and was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Ngay;</hi> and now being licenſed to the degree of Doctor, he went to <hi>Pequin.</hi> But when he read in a certain book writ by a Doctor of <hi>China,</hi> concerning the European affairs, That our fathers are not <hi>Saracens,</hi> and know no God but the Lord of heaven, and earth; and would perſwade himſelf that ours did profeſſe the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> he went into the Church with <hi>P. Matthaeus Riccius.</hi> On an altar there was the effigies of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the childe Jeſus, whom St. <hi>John</hi> his fore-runner worſhipped with bended knees; now that day was the holy-day of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt. The Jew thinking it was the effigies of <hi>Rebecca,</hi> and her two ſons <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> he bowed alſo to the Image, but with this apology, that he worſhipped no Images, but that he could not but honour theſe who were the parents of our Nation. And he asking if the foure Evangeliſts on both ſides of the altar, were not foure of the twelue ſons of <hi>Jacob;</hi> the Jeſuite anſwered,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112444:27"/>Yes, thinking he had asked of the 12. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. But afterward the Jew acknowledged to the Jeſuite that he was an Iſraelite; and he found the Kings Bible, and acknowledged the Hebrew letters, though he could not read them. By this occaſion our people learnt, that ten or twelve families of Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites were there, and had built a very neat Synagogue which coſt 10000. crowns; in which they have kept the five books of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> with great veneration for 600. yeers. He alſo affirmed, that in <hi>Hamcheu</hi> the metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis of the Province <hi>Chequiona,</hi> there are far more families, with a ſynagogue; and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where that many families live without a ſynagogue, becauſe that by little and little they are extinguiſhed. He relating many things out of the old Teſtament, he differed but little in pronouncing thoſe names. He ſaid, that ſome among them were not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Hebrew tongue, but that himſelf had neglected it, having ſtudied the China tongue from a childe. For which cauſe he was counted almoſt unworthy of their ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by the ruler of the ſynagogue. But he chiefly looked after this, that he might get to be Doctor. Three yeers after <hi>P. Matthaeus Riccius</hi> ſent one of our brethren to that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis, who found all thoſe things true.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112444:28"/>He compared the beginnings, and endings of the books which the Jews keep in their ſynagogue, with our Pentateuch, and ſaw no difference, this onely, that thoſe had no pricks. The other Jeſuite is <hi>Alfonſus Cimedro,</hi> who likewiſe ſaith, that there is a great number of Jews in the Province of <hi>Oroenſis,</hi> on the Weſt part of <hi>China,</hi> who know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the coming, and ſuffering of Jeſus. And he from thence gathers, that they are of the ten Tribes, (which opinion I alſo am of) becauſe thoſe Chineſes obſerve many Jewiſh rites, which you may ſee in a manuſcript, which the noble <hi>Jaochimus Wicofortius</hi> hath. And why might not ſome of them ſail from <hi>China</hi> to <hi>New-Spaine</hi> through the Streight between <hi>China,</hi> and <hi>Anian,</hi> and <hi>Quivira,</hi> which do border upon <hi>New-Spain;</hi> and from thence they went to the Iſles of <hi>Panama, Peru,</hi> and thoſe thereabout. Theſe in my judgement are thoſe Chineſes of whom <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks, Chap. 49. ver: 12. (treating about Iſraels return to his countrey) <hi>Behold theſe ſhall come from afar, and theſe from the North, and from the Weſt, and theſe from the land of Sinim.</hi> And ſo <hi>Ptolomy in lib</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>tab.</hi> 11. cals it, The countrey of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim, or Sina: and this is the true ſenſe of the words; <hi>Aben Ezra</hi> therefore is miſtaken, who derives it of Sene, a buſh, or wood, which he placeth in Aegypt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:112444:28"/>
               <head>SECT: XVII.</head>
               <p>I Could eaſily believe, that the 10. Tribes as they increaſed in number, ſo they ſpread into more Provinces before-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and into <hi>Tartary.</hi> For <hi>Abraham Ortelius</hi> in his Geography of the world, and map of <hi>Tartary,</hi> he notes the place of the Danites, which he calls the Hord, which is the ſame which the Hebrew <hi>Jerida,</hi> ſignifying <hi>A de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent.</hi> And lower, he mentions the Hord of <hi>Naphtali,</hi> poſſeſſed by <hi>Peroza</hi> in the year 476. <hi>Schikhardus</hi> in his Tarich, or ſeries of the Kings of <hi>Perſia,</hi> amplifies the hiſtory of this war, where <hi>ex lib.</hi> 4. of <hi>Agathias</hi> he thus ſaith, <hi>A little after when they were eaſed of that plague,</hi> (<hi>ſc.</hi> 7. years drought) <hi>in the time of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Zeno, Firuz made a double war with Naphta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, in which at laſt he was deſtroyed. For firſt of all he was brought to the ſtreights of places unknown; who then ſought for peace upon this condition (and obtained it) that he ſhould ſwear that he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after provoke them; and that he ſhould do reverence to this Conquerer in token of ſubjection: which afterward by the counſell of the Magicians he performed craftily, for he bowed towards the Eaſtern Sun, that his own people might think that he bowed rather to the Sun (after his Countrey cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome) then to honour his Enemy. But he did not
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112444:29"/>truly perform that firſt agreement, though confirmed by Letters Patents; who becauſe he could not digeſt the diſgrace of bowing to his Enemy, he prepared a new Army and went againſt them; but a ſecond time he being entrapped by the badneſſe of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, he loſt his life, and many with him, in a gulf which the Nephthalites had prepared for him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving dreſſed it over with reeds, and ſome earth thrown a top; they having left in the middle ſome high grounds, and trees where their Souts were, that their ſtratageme might not be found, and that the Perſians might more confidently attempt the ditch. Thus a raſh King paid for his perfidy, he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling more in daring, then in counſell, as Agathias ſaith. The Patent by which peace had been agreed, was hung upon a ſpear, and might be ſeen of him at diſtance, that he might remember his oath, repent, and diſiſt from his enterpriſe: but he cared little for that. But when by his unexpected fall he ſaw he ſhould die, it is ſaid that he pulled off from his right ear a pearl of huge bigneſſe, and whiteneſſe, and leſt any after him ſhould finde it (more likely that his carps ſhould not be known) he threw it a great way off.</hi> The ſame Author asks, who thoſe <hi>Neph<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thalites</hi> were? and by many arguments he proves that they are the relicks of the Jews; ſaith he, I do wholly think that they are the relicks of the Jews of the tribe of Nephtali, whom Triglath Pileſſer the Aſſirian carried into thoſe places, in <hi>2</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:112444:29"/>King. <hi>15.29.</hi> For <hi>1.</hi> The name, in the beſt copies of Agathias, which Lewenclavius hath mended, is the ſame fully; in other books it wants nothing but an (b); now it is ſearce poſſible that in a word of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſyllables that ſhould fall out by chance. <hi>2.</hi> Their countenance diſcovers it, for as Procopious J C ſaith they are not black, or foule in their countenance, as the Huns are among whom they live, but the onely white men of that countrey; that it may evidently appear that they came from ſome other place thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>3.</hi> Their manners agree, for the ſame. Author ſaith, that they are not Nomades, as the Huns who are unconſtant in their dwelling, and eat up one place after another; but they inhabit one certain place. Beſide, they obſerve Law and equity, as the Romanes; and have pollicy, being well governed by their Prince: both which is rare among their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Nations. Alſo they do not lay abroad their dead, as the Barbarians do, but they deſently cover them with earth. Laſtly their jornals do teſtifie that many Jews live there, eſpecially in the mountains, who have ſearched to the mid-land countreys of Eaſt-Aſia. R. Benjamin. f. <hi>23.</hi> From thence (the coaſt of Perſia) is <hi>28</hi> daies journey to the mountains Niſebor, which are neer the river Gozan. The Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralites which come from thence into Perſia, ſay, that there in the Cities of Niſebor, are <hi>4.</hi> Tribes (ſo: Dan, Zabulon, Aſer. Naphtali,) of the firſt captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which Shalmaneſer the Aſſyrian carried thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:112444:30"/>as in <hi>2</hi> King <hi>17.6.</hi> he brought them to Habor, and Halab, the river Gozan, and the mountains of Media. The compaſſe of that countrey is <hi>20.</hi> daies j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urney; and they poſſeſſe Cities, and Caſtles upon the mountains, by one ſide of which, runs the river Gozan; neither are they ſubject to the Nations, but have a Governor over them, by name R. Joſeph A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markela a Levite, and there are among them ſome who ſtudy wiſdom. They ſowe; and reap; yea they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rage war to the Countrey of Cuth. <hi>In the ſame place</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>telius <hi>addes, in the countrey Tabor, or Tibur</hi> (<hi>which</hi> Solinus <hi>commends, in</hi> c. <hi>49.</hi>) <hi>they dwell a people, who though they have loſt the holy writings, they obey one King; who came into France, in</hi> Ann. <hi>1530. and ſpoke with</hi> Francis <hi>the firſt, was burnt at Mantua by the command of the Emperour</hi> Charles <hi>the fifth, becauſe that he did private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reach Judaiſm to Chriſtian Princes, and to the Emperour himſelf.</hi> Boterus <hi>ſaith the ſame in his relations of the fartheſt part of Tartary. But both theſe were deceived; for</hi> Rabbinus Jeſephus Cohon, <hi>a man worthy to be believed, relates this more truly in his Chronology, ſaying, that the Jew who came out of that countrey, was the brother of the King of the Iſraelites, was called</hi> David <hi>the Reubenite; and having ſeen India in his paſſage, he came to Portugal, where he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:112444:30"/>the Kings Secretary to Judaiſm, who fled from thence with him, taking the name of</hi> Selomoh Molho; <hi>he in ſhort time was ſo well verſed in the Law, yea in the</hi> Cabala <hi>it ſelf, that he made all</hi> Italy <hi>admire him. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary together with the Rendenite, ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to draw the Pope,</hi> Charles <hi>the fifth, and</hi> Francis <hi>the firſt to Judaiſm.</hi> Selomoh Molho <hi>was taken at</hi> Mantua, <hi>and burnt alive, in the year 1540. He yet was offered his life, if he would turn Chriſtian. The Reubenite was by</hi> Charles <hi>the fifth carried priſoner into</hi> Spain, <hi>where he ſhortly after died.</hi> Abraham Friſol Orhotolam <hi>remembers the Reubenite, ſaying, 45. years agone</hi> David Reubenita, <hi>a Prince of the Iſraelites, came from</hi> Tabor, <hi>a Province of</hi> Tartary, <hi>into</hi> Europe, <hi>who ſaid that two Tribes are there; and other Tribes a little farther, under their Kings, and Princes, and alſo an unſpeakable number of people. Perhaps the Province Tabor is the ſame that Habor; which is mentioned in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> King. <hi>17.6. that the ten Tribes were brough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> by</hi> Salmaneſer <hi>to Habor, and Halah; now the Hebrew letters (h) and (t) are neer in faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Eldad Danita <hi>of the Tribe of</hi> Dan, <hi>came out of thoſe Countreys 500. years agon</hi> (<hi>a letter from whom, which we call</hi> Sephar El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dod a-Dani, <hi>is kept to this day</hi>) <hi>and being
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112444:31"/>examined by the Rabbins, was found an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved man. The learned Rabbi</hi> David Kim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hi, <hi>who lived 450. years ſince, in</hi> etymol. ſuo <hi>in the word</hi> Segiah, <hi>he ſaith,</hi> Rabbi Jonah writes of the name of Rabbi Juda Aben Karis, that he heard Eldad Danita ſay, &amp;c. <hi>And ſo what I ſaid is true, as appears by the teſtimonies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XVIII.</head>
               <p>PArt of the ten Tribes alſo live in <hi>Ethiopia</hi> in the Habyſſin Kingdom; as divers Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſſins reported at <hi>Rome. Boterus</hi> in his relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſpeaks the ſame thing, that two potent Nations do live neer <hi>Nilus,</hi> and that one of them is that of the Iſraelites, who are gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a mighty King. A Coſmographer who hath added notes to <hi>Ptolomyes</hi> tables, ſaith thus in his table of New Africa; that part of new Africk was unknown of old, the head of <hi>Nilus</hi> not being known, which is in the mountains of the Moon, as the Ancients call them; where there dwels a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Iſraelites, paying tribute to <hi>Preſter John. Rabbi Abraham Friſol</hi> in the book al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready quoted, ſaith, that in his time ſome who had been in thoſe Countreys, reported the ſame to <hi>Hercules</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ferraria.</hi> And without queſtion from hence the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſſins
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112444:31"/>learned circumciſion, the obſervation of the Sabbath, and many more Jewiſh rites. Of theſe <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſeems to ſpeak, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 18.1, 2. <hi>Wo to the land which under the ſhadow of ſails doth ſail beyond the rivers of Ethiopia, by whom</hi> (the Prophet ſaith) <hi>are ſent ambaſſadors in ſhips of bulruſhes,</hi> (ſuch as the Ethiopians uſe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Almadiae.) <hi>Bring back a people driven out of their countrey, and torn, and more miſerable then any among us. Gifts ſhall be brought to the Lord of Sebaoth, in the place where the name of the Lord of Sebaoth, is worſhipped, in the mount Sion.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Zephany</hi> ſaith the ſame, in <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9, 10. <hi>Then will I give to the people that they ſpeaking a pure language, may all call upon the name of God, whom they ſhall ſerve with reverence; from beyond the rivers of Ethiopia they ſhall bring to me for a giſt, Hatray</hi> the daughter of my diſperſed ones, (that is, the Nations of <hi>Ethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opia</hi>). Which agrees with that of <hi>Iſa. And your brethren</hi> (which are the 10. Tribes) <hi>ſhall bring gifts to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XIX.</head>
               <p>ANd without doubt they alſo dwell in <hi>Media;</hi> from thence they paſſed <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates,</hi> whither they were firſt brought, as in 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.24. and in the book of <hi>Tobit. Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> alſo ſpeaks of them in the Preface of his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:112444:32"/>book of the War of the Jews, that the Jews did think that their brethren, who dwelt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and farther, would rebell againſt the Romanes. <hi>Agrippa</hi> in his oration to the people of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that they would not rebell againſt the Romanes, ſpeaks thus, What aſſociates do ye expect to joyn with you, in your rebellion, and war? doth not all the known world pay tribute to the <hi>Romans?</hi> Perhaps ſome of ye hope to have help from them beyond <hi>Euphrates.</hi> And in <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit. c.</hi> 5. ſpeaking of thoſe who in the time of <hi>Ezra</hi> returned from <hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>All Iſrael dwelt in Media; for two Tribes only dwelt in Aſia, and Europe, and lived ſubject to the Romans; as the other ten on the other ſide En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates, where they are ſo many, that they cannot be counted.</hi> It is not therfore to be doubted, the people encreaſing after their firſt tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they ſought out new places, which we have formerly mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XX.</head>
               <p>LAſtly, all think, that part of the ten Tribes dwell beyond the river <hi>Sabbathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or ſabbaticall. <hi>Rabbi Johanan</hi> the Author of the <hi>Jeruſalem Talmud,</hi> who lived 160 years after the deſtruction of the 2d: Temple, ſaith in his treatiſe of the Sanhedrim, <hi>ca.</hi> 17. That
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112444:32"/>the 10. Tribes were carried into 3. places, <hi>ſc.</hi> to the Sabbaticall river, to <hi>Daphne</hi> the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs of <hi>Antioch,</hi> and thither where a cloud comes down and covers them: and that they ſhall be redeemed from thoſe three places; for ſo he opens that place of <hi>Iſa:</hi> Chap. 49.9. <hi>That they may ſay to the captives, go forth,</hi> (<hi>ſc:</hi> to them who were at the Sabbaticall river) <hi>to them that are in darkneſſe, ſhew your ſelves,</hi> (<hi>ſc:</hi> to them who are compaſſed with the cloud) <hi>and to all, they ſhall be refreſhed in the wayes,</hi> (<hi>ſc:</hi> to them who live in <hi>Daphne</hi> of <hi>Antioch</hi> which is in <hi>Syria</hi>). Whence you may obſerve, that the learned man <hi>l'Emperiur</hi> tranſlated it ill, <hi>at the ſides of Antioch,</hi> whereas <hi>Daphne</hi> is the proper name of a pleaſant grove near <hi>Antioch. Sedar olam</hi> makes mention of that cloud, and cals them <hi>mountains of obſcurity.</hi> And in <hi>Talmud tractat. Sanhedr. c.</hi> 11. <hi>R. Jonathan ben <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ziel,</hi> who lived an hundred yeers before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: Temple, in <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.10. where the Lord ſaith, <hi>I will do wonders before all thy people, ſuch as were never done in the whole earth, or in any Nation,</hi> &amp;c. and he refers all thoſe things to the tranſportation of the people. <hi>He ſhall draw them to the rivers of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, and ſhall carry them to the ſabbaticall river, and ſhall teach them, that thoſe miracles were never performed to any Nation of the known world.</hi> Our
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:112444:33"/>ancient Rabbins in <hi>Bereſit Rabba</hi> (no mean book) in <hi>Peraſach,</hi> do ſay, that <hi>Tornunfus</hi> ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how it ſhould appear that the day which we keep, is the 7th. day, on which God reſted after the Creation of the world: <hi>Rabbi Aque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bah</hi> (who lived 52. yeers after the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: Temple) anſwered by an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taken from the ſtones of the Sabbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call river, which in the ſix dayes are toſſed up and down with a continuall motion, but do reſt on the Sabbath day, and move not. The ſame is ſaid in the <hi>Babylonian Talmud, tractat. Sanhed. c. 7. &amp; in Tanuah Peraſach. c. 9. In eodem Bereſit Raba, in Peraſach</hi> 37. <hi>Rabbi Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ten Tribes were carried to the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baticall river, but Juda and Benjamin are diſperſed into all Countreys</hi> In <hi>Aſirim Raba,</hi> the laſt verſe of the Song, its ſaid, <hi>Our bed is flouriſhing;</hi> that it is meant the ten Tribes, which were carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Sabbaticall river; and that river running all the week, doth cauſe the ten Tribes there remaining to be ſhut up; for though on the 7th. day the river doth reſt, yet it is forbidden by our Law to take a jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney then; and for that reaſon they remained there miraculouſly, as loſt, and concealed from us. So that of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. <hi>That they ſay to the priſoners, go forth,</hi> is interpreted of them in <hi>Jalcut. R. Aquebah</hi> after the ſame manner
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112444:33"/>explains that of <hi>Levit.</hi> 36.38. <hi>And ye ſhall periſh among the heathen.</hi> And that of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. <hi>ult. and they ſhall come, who were ready to periſh in Aſſyria.</hi> Becauſe they are remote from the reſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another Rabbi in Bamibar <hi>Raba Paraſa</hi> 16. applyes to them that of <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.12. <hi>Behold them who come from far:</hi> that ſo all thoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors mention that River. The teſtimony of <hi>Joſephus</hi> is famous, <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>de Bel. Jud. ca.</hi> 24. ſaying, <hi>The Emperour Titus paſſing between Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, and Raphanea, Cities of King Agrippa, he ſaw the wonderfull River, which though it be ſwift, yet it is dry on every ſeventh day; and that day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſt, it reſumes its ordinary courſe, as if it had no change; and it always obſerves this order. It is called Sabbaticall, from the ſolemn feaſt of the Jews, becauſe it imitates their reſt every ſeventh day.</hi> I know ſome do otherwiſe expound thoſe words of <hi>Joſephus,</hi> but they hit not his meaning, as appears by this, that he cals the River, Sabbathio, or ſabbaticall: which word cannot be derived but from Sabbath; and who doth not ſee that it ceaſeth to flow, or move, on the Sabbath day; and ſo <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> muſt be underſtood according to my ſenſe. <hi>Pliny</hi> alſo confirms this opinion, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Nat: hiſt. c.</hi> 2. he ſaith, <hi>In Judea a river lyes dry every Sabbath;</hi> yet I think <hi>Pliny</hi> is deceived, and ill informed, when he ſaith it is a river
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:112444:34"/>in Judea; neither is it to be found in Judea, but in another place, where many Jews live. <hi>R. Selomoh Jarchi</hi> who lived 540. yeers ſince, mentions that River in <hi>Comment. Talm.</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, The ſtones, and ſand of that River do continually move all the ſix dayes of the week, untill the ſeventh <hi>R. Mardochus Japhe</hi> in his learned book <hi>Jephe Thoar</hi> ſaith, The <hi>Arabians</hi> derive Sabbathion from the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, who uſe to adde the particle (ion) to adjectives. The ſame ſaith, that it was told him of an hour-glaſſe filled with the ſand of <hi>Sabbathion,</hi> which ran all the week till the Sabbath. And I heard the ſame from my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; which teſtimony I account as good, as if I ſaw it my ſelf; (for fathers do not uſe to impoſe upon their ſons.) He told me that there was an Arabian at <hi>Lisborn,</hi> who had ſuch an hour-glaſſe; and that every Friday at evening he would walk in the ſtreet called the new ſtreet, and ſhew this glaſſe to Jews who counterfeited Chriſtianity, and ſay, <hi>Ye Jews, ſhut up your ſhops, for now the Sabbath comes.</hi> Another worthy of credit, told me of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hour-glaſſe, which he had ſome years before, before the port <hi>Mysketa.</hi> He ſaw him by chance (or the Judge of the place) paſſing that way from <hi>Cadez,</hi> and being asked, what he was? he commanded him to be taken
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:112444:34"/>away; rebuking the Mahometans that by this mean they did confirm the Jewiſh Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. I ſhould not ſpeak of theſe glaſſes, if the authority of ſuch a man whom I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, did not move me; though I beleeve that God did not onely work that miracle, that he might keep part of the 10. Tribes there, but other alſo, as you may ſee in <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras. R. Moſes Gerundenſis</hi> a learned Cabaliſt, and Interpreter of the Law in <hi>Paraſa Aazinu,</hi> thinks the river Sabbathion to be the ſame with Gozan, of <hi>Guz,</hi> which ſignifies, to ſnatch away, becauſe except the 7th. day, on all the other, it carries with it, by its ſwiftneſſe, the very ſtones. Of this there is mention in 2 <hi>King.</hi> whither the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> led his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptives; and ſo relates <hi>Benjamin Tudelenſis</hi> in his journall, that part of the 10 Tribes dwelt at the bank of that River. But I know not where the river G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zan is. In the yeer 5394. that is, 15 years agon, in the City <hi>Lubin,</hi> two <hi>Polonians</hi> after they had travelled long, they wrot in Ducht a book of the originall of the Sabbaticall river, but the Senate command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to be burnt at the Mart of Breſlaw, by the perſwaſion of the Jeſuites. <hi>Abraham Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal</hi> in his Orchot Olam, <hi>c.</hi> 26. will have this river to be in <hi>India,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>The head of the Sabbaticall river is in the countrey of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper India,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:112444:35"/>among the rivers of Ganges.</hi> And a little after, <hi>The ſabbaticall river hath its originall from the other ſide of Kalikout</hi> (which lies far above the bound of <hi>Lamik,</hi> which he placeth beyond the <hi>ſinus Barbaricus</hi>) <hi>and it parts the Indians from the kingdom of the Jews, which river you may certainly finde there.</hi> Though he takes <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan</hi> for <hi>Ganges,</hi> for ſome nearneſſe of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; yet its not to be doubted that in that place there are many Jews, witneſſe <hi>Joannes de Bairos</hi> in his Decads. <hi>Eldad Danita</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the 4. Tribes, which he placeth at <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zan,</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Sabbaticall river is among them. Joſephus</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Titus</hi> ſaw the ſabbathion between <hi>Arca,</hi> and <hi>Raphanea.</hi> Which teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeems the truer, becauſe its not to be thought that <hi>Joſephus</hi> would tella lie of him, by whom be might be rebuked. I think that ye muſt look for it not far from the Caſpian Sea: &amp; I am not alone in this opinion. What ever it be, it appears that this river is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and that part of the 10. Tribes are hid there; and I may ſay with <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.28, 29. <hi>And the Lord caſt them out of their land in anger, and in wrath; Secret things belong to the Lord our God.</hi> For it is not known when they ſhall return to their Countrey, neither can it perfectly be ſhewed where they are, God ſuffering it, as its ſaid in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.26. <hi>I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:112444:35"/>to caſt them forth unto the ends of the earth, and to make their remembrance ceaſe from among men.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, I will caſt them unto the fartheſt places of the world, that none may remember them; and therfore they are truly in Scripture called <hi>impriſoned,</hi> and <hi>loſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXI.</head>
               <p>NEither is there weight in the argument which ſome have brought to me, if they be in the world, why do we not know them better? There are many things which we know, and yet know not their originall; are we not to this day ignorant of the heads of the foure Rivers, <hi>Nilus, Ganges, Euphrates,</hi> and <hi>Tigris?</hi> alſo there are many unknown Countreys. Beſide, though ſome live in known, and neighbour Countreys, yet they are unknown by being behinde mountains; ſo it happened under the reign of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and <hi>Iſabel,</hi> that ſome Spaniards were found out by accident, at <hi>Batueca,</hi> belonging to the Duke of <hi>Alva,</hi> which place is diſtant but 10. miles from <hi>Salamanca,</hi> and neer to <hi>Placen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> whither ſome Spaniards fled, when the <hi>Moores</hi> poſſeſſed <hi>Spaine,</hi> and dwelt there 800. years. If therefore a people could lye hid ſo long in the middle of <hi>Spaine,</hi> why may we not ſay that thoſe are hid, whom God will
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:112444:36"/>not have any perfectly to know, before the end of daies?</p>
               <p>And theſe things we have gathered con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the habitations of the ten Tribes, who, we beleeve, do ſtill keep the Jewiſh rites, as in 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.26. when the Iſraelites were carried captive by <hi>Salmaneſer,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Cuthah</hi> came in their ſtead, an Iſraelitiſh Prieſt was ſent by the King, to teach them, becauſe Lions infeſted them, for that they were ignorant that there was another wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip uſed in the land: but when the Prieſt ſaw that it was impoſſible to take that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wholly off from idolatry, he permitted them to worſhip divers gods, ſo that they would acknowledge one to be the mover of all things. The ſame is alſo ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of all the Hiſtories which we have alleaged. And our brethren do keep the Law more zealouſly out of their land, than in it, as being neither ambitious, nor contentious (which hath ſometimes hapned with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>David</hi>) by which means they might eaſily erre in the true Religion, not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and withdraw that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which is due to the Lord, and to his Temple.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:112444:36"/>
               <head>SECT: XXII.</head>
               <p>VVE learn out of the firſt of <hi>Ezra,</hi> that none of the 10. Tribes entred the ſecond Temple; for it is ſaid that only ſome of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> and ſome of <hi>Benjamin</hi> did return. <hi>Ezra</hi> alſo ſaith the ſame in the 1 of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> that <hi>Salmaneſer</hi> carried the 10. Tribes to <hi>Hala, Habor,</hi> and <hi>Hara,</hi> and to the river <hi>Gozan</hi> to this day: ſo that you may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that at that time they were there. So likewiſe <hi>Joſephus in Antiq. Jud. lib.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>Perhaps ſome will ſay, ſince <hi>Media,</hi> and <hi>Perſia</hi> are near to <hi>Bahylon,</hi> why did they not return to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with the two Tribes? I anſwer, becauſe ſo few of the 2. neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Tribes did return from thence to <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> for that they were well ſeated in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> or elſe becauſe they heard the Prophets ſay, that they muſt not look for any redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption but that which was to be at the end of daies. How then can we think that they, who were more remote, and alſo had learnt the ſame things of the Prophets, ſhould leave their place, perhaps to ſuffer new miſeries, and calamities? Beſide, we do not read that <hi>Cyrus</hi> gave leave to any to return, but onely to the two Tribes of <hi>Juda</hi> and <hi>Benjamin.</hi> And alſo it is probable (as ſome Authors affirm)
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:112444:37"/>that they could not go up from thence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they had continually wars with the neighbour people.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXIII.</head>
               <p>HItherto we have ihewed that the ten Tribes are in divers places, as in the Weſt-Indies; in <hi>Sina;</hi> in the confines of <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry;</hi> beyond the river <hi>Sabbathion,</hi> and <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes;</hi> in <hi>Media;</hi> in the kingdom of the Habyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins; of all which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> is to be underſtood, in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.11. <hi>It ſhall come to paſſe in that day, that the Lord ſhall ſet his hand the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time to recover the remnant of his people, which ſhall be left from Aſſyria, from Egypt, from Pathros, from Ethiopia, from Elam, from Sinear, from Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>math, and from the Iſlands of the Sea.</hi> From whence you may gather, that it is meant of thoſe places where the ten Tribes dwell. <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhall be the two places of their generall meeting; as more fully hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pathros,</hi> is not <hi>Peluſium,</hi> nor <hi>Petra,</hi> but <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia,</hi> neer to the Caſpian Sea, where I think, with many others, the Sabbaticall river is. Although there is a <hi>Pathros</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> as the learned <hi>Samuel Bochardus</hi> ſaith in his holy Geography.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chus,</hi> according to common opinion, is <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> as is proved out of <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.23. and in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:112444:37"/>this place of <hi>Ieremy</hi> are meant the Iſraelites, who live in the Countrey of the Abyſſins.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elam,</hi> is a Province in <hi>Perſia,</hi> as it appears in <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.2. where are deſert places, in which, perhaps, the remnant of the ten Tribes is.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shinar,</hi> is a Province about <hi>Babylon,</hi> as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.10. where <hi>Babel</hi> is ſaid to be in <hi>Shinar;</hi> and <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.2. it is ſaid, that <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> carried the holy veſſels to the land of <hi>Shinar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hamath,</hi> there are many Hamaths menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in the Scripture, many underſtand it of <hi>Antioch;</hi> but becauſe Geographers reckon up 12. places named <hi>Antioch,</hi> therefore we can affirm nothing for certain; but I think, that that is meant, which is placed in <hi>Scythia.</hi> The ſeventy Interpreters by <hi>Hamath,</hi> underſtand the Sun, from <hi>Hamath</hi> the Sun; and they tranſlate it, From the riſing of the Sun; and I think it is no ill tranſlation; for hereby all the Iſraelites who are in greater <hi>Aſia, India,</hi> and <hi>Sina,</hi> may be underſtood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Iſlands of the Sea;</hi> ſo almoſt all tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate it; but I think it is to be rendred, The Iſlands of the Weſt, for <hi>I am</hi> in holy Scripture ſignifies <hi>The Weſt,</hi> as in <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.14. and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other places; and upon this account thoſe Iſraelites are implyed, who are Weſtward from the Holy Land, among whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericans are.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:112444:38"/>
               <head>SECT: XXIIII.</head>
               <p>THe Prophet adds in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.12. <hi>And he ſhall ſet up a ſign for the Nations, and he ſhall aſſemble the out-caſts-of Iſrael, and gather together the diſperſed of Judah from the foure quarters of the earth.</hi> Where he notes two things: 1. that he cals the Iſraelites <hi>out-caſts,</hi> but the Jews <hi>ſcattered;</hi> and the reaſon is, becauſe the ten Tribes are not onely far off from the Holy Land, but alſo they live in the extremities and ends of Countreys; from whence the Prophet cals them <hi>caſt out.</hi> But he doth not ſay, that the Iſraelites are to be gathered from the foure quarters of the earth, becauſe they are not ſo diſperſed through the world, as the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> is, which now hath ſynagogues, not onely in three parts of the world, but alſo in <hi>America</hi> The Prophet adds in <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>The envy alſo of Ephraim ſhall depart, and the adverſaries of Judah ſhall be cut off.</hi> For then there ſhall be no contention between <hi>Judah,</hi> and the 10. Tribes, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended under the name <hi>Ephraim,</hi> becauſe their firſt King <hi>Jeroboam</hi> was of that Tribe. And then, as it is in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.22. <hi>One King ſhall be King over them all, and they ſhall be no more two Nations, neither ſhall they be divided any more into two kingdoms.</hi> There ſhall be one
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:112444:38"/>King to them both, of the family of <hi>David.</hi> Alſo the Lord at the redemption will drie up <hi>Nilus,</hi> and <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and will divide it into ſeven ſtreames (anſwerable to his dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the red Sea when they came out of <hi>Egypt</hi>) perhaps that the ſeven Tribes, which are in thoſe parts, may go over it; as they paſſe into their Countrey, as <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ſaith in ch. 27.12, 13. <hi>And it ſhall be in that day, and he ſhall ſhake off from the bank of the river</hi> (ſome underſtand <hi>Euphrates</hi>) <hi>unto the river of Egypt</hi> (Nilus) <hi>and ye, O children of Iſrael, ſhall be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered one by one.</hi> Which was never done in the captivity of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith in chap. 11.11. <hi>that he will return them the ſecond time,</hi> &amp;c. Now the redemption from <hi>Babylon,</hi> cannot be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſuch an one, becauſe all of them were not brought back to their Countey. But the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption ſhall be univerſal to all the tribes, as it was when they went out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> which redemption ſhall be like the firſt in many things, as I ſhew in the third part of my <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciler;</hi> and ſo it may be called the ſecond, in reference to that firſt from Aegypt. Whence <hi>Ieremiah</hi> ſaith, Chap. 23.7, 8. <hi>That then it ſhall not be ſaid, He that brought Iſrael out of Egypt, but from the North, and from all countreys, whither he had driven them.</hi> That they ſhall not mention
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:112444:39"/>their departure from Aegypt, for the cauſe fore-mentioned.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XXV.</head>
               <p>THe ſame Prophet, <hi>ſc: Iſa.</hi> 43.5, 6. ſaith, <hi>I will bring thy ſeed from the Eaſt, and will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thee from the Weſt: I will ſay to the North, Give up; and to the South, Keep not back; bring my ſons from far, and my daughters from the ends of the earth.</hi> For <hi>Media, Perſia,</hi> and <hi>China,</hi> lye on the Eaſt; <hi>Tartary</hi> and <hi>Scythia</hi> on the North; the kingdom of the Abyſſins on the South; <hi>Europe</hi> on the Weſt, from the Holy Land. But when he ſaith, <hi>Bring ye my ſons from far,</hi> he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands <hi>America;</hi> ſo that in thoſe verſes he underſtands all thoſe places, in which the Tribes are detained. Alſo in Chap. 49. from ver: 7. to the end of the Chapter, he ſaith, that that return ſhall be moſt happy. And in ch: 56. ver: 8. God ſaith, <hi>He that gathers the out-caſts of Iſrael.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah</hi> in ch: 33. ver: 16. <hi>In thoſe days ſhall Iudah be ſaved, and Ieruſalem ſhall dwell ſafely.</hi> It is certain, and <hi>Ierom</hi> aſſents to all our Authors, that when <hi>Iudah</hi> is joyned with Iſrael, by Iſrael the ten Tribes are meant. The ſame addes in ch: 31. ver. 15. in the comforting of <hi>Rahel,</hi> who wept for the carrying away her ſons <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> the firſt by <hi>Salmaneſer</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:112444:39"/>into Aſſyria, the laſt by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> into Babylon, he ſaith, in ver: 16. <hi>Refrain thy voice from weeping, and thine eyes from tears, for thy work ſhall be rewarded.</hi> And it follows in Cha. 33. ver. 7. <hi>And I will cauſe the captivity of Iudah, and the captivity of Iſrael to return, and I wil build them up as at the firſt. Ezekiel</hi> ſaith the ſame in Chap. 34.13. and in Chap. 37.16. under the figure of two ſticks, on which were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the names of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Ephraim,</hi> by which he proves the gathering together of the twelve Tribes to be ſubject to <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Son of <hi>David;</hi> in ver. 22. he ſaith, <hi>And one king ſhall be King to them all;</hi> according as <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith in Chap. 2. So alſo ſaith <hi>Amos</hi> in ch: 9. ver. 14, 15. <hi>And I will bring again the captivity of my people Iſrael, and they ſhall build the waste cities, and inhabite them; and they ſhall plant vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, and drink the wine thereof: they ſhall make gardens, and eat the fruit of them. And they ſhall he no more pulled up out of their land which I have given them, ſaith the Lord thy God.</hi> So alſo <hi>Mica</hi> in ch: 2.12. <hi>I will ſurely aſſemble, O Jacob, all of thee, I will gather the remnant of Iſrael, I will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo place him as the flack in the ſheep-fold.</hi> For that in the captivity of <hi>Babylon</hi> all were not ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together. The Prophet <hi>Zechariah</hi> in ch: 8.7. and in ch: 10.6. and all the reſt of the Prophets do witneſſe the ſame thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:112444:40"/>
               <head>SECT: XXVI.</head>
               <p>BUt which way that redemption ſhall be, no man can tell; but onely ſo far as we may gather out of the Prophets, That at that time the ten Tribes ſhall come to Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem under the leading of a Prince, whom ſome Rabbins in the <hi>Talmud,</hi> and in ſome places of the Chaldy paraphraſe, do call <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> and elſewhere <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ephraim;</hi> who being ſlain in the laſt war of <hi>Gog,</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> ſhall ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>David,</hi> who ſhall be, as <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſay, <hi>The everlasting Prince of all the twelve Tribes.</hi> Our wiſe men do, in many places, eſpecially in the Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Talmud, <hi>in tract. ſuca. c.</hi> 5. make mention of that <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ephraim;</hi> where they ſay, that he ſhall dye in the laſt war of <hi>Gog,</hi> and <hi>Magog;</hi> and they ſo expound that of <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>And they ſhall look upon me whom they have pierced, and they ſhall mourn for him, as one mourneth for his onely ſon.</hi> They adde alſo, that the foure captains, of whom the ſame Prophet ſpeaks in ch. 11. are, <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>David, Meſſiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Elias,</hi> and the high Prieſt; which foure are thoſe dignities, which ſhall ſhew their power in that bleſſed age. Obſerve, that
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:112444:40"/>ſometime they cal <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſometime of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> for he ſhall come out of the Tribe of <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and ſhall be Captain of all the 10. Tribes, who give their name to <hi>Ephraim,</hi> becauſe that their firſt King <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> was of that Tribe. Not without cauſe do they call him the ſon of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> for he was the true type of the houſe of Iſrael, in his impriſonment, and future happineſs. Add to this, that he was ſo long hid from his brethren, that they did not know him: as in like manner the ten Tribes are at this day, who are led captive, but hereafter ſhall come to the top of felicity, in the ſame manner as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did. That <hi>Meſſiah</hi> of <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſhall dye in the battel of <hi>Gog,</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> and afterward ſhall riſe again, that he may enjoy the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, not of a kingly Scepter, but the office onely of a Vice-roy, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> in <hi>Egypt;</hi> for that the Empire of the houſe of Iſrael fell, under the reign of <hi>Hoſea</hi> the ſon of <hi>Elah;</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> ſaith in ch. 5.2. Therefore the Kingdom of the 10. Tribes ſhall not be reſtored, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaith in ch. 37. under the reign of <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>David,</hi> who ſhall be everlaſting; and by the death of <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the ſon of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> the 10. Tribes ſhall ſee, that God will not that they ſhould have more Kings then one. As its already ſpoken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:112444:41"/>
               <head>SECT: XXVII.</head>
               <p>THoſe Tribes then ſhal be gathered from all quarters of the earth, into Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys near to the Holy Land; namely, into <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and <hi>Egypt;</hi> and from thence they ſhall go into their Countrey; of which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks, in ch. 27.13. <hi>And it ſhall be in that day, that the great trumpet ſhall be blown, and they who were loſt, ſhall come into the land of Aſſyria; and they who were caſt out, into Egypt; and ſhall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Lord in the holy mount at Ieruſalem.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, as trumpets ſound, to call any army together: ſo they ſhall come together, who were dead (that is, diſperſed through all <hi>Aſia</hi>) into <hi>Aſſyria;</hi> and the out-caſts (that is, which are in <hi>America</hi>) ſhall come by the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea to <hi>Alexandria</hi> of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and in the like manner thoſe who are in <hi>Africa,</hi> when <hi>Nilus</hi> ſhall be dried up, and <hi>Euphrates</hi> ſhall be divided; as we have already ſaid. And becauſe the gathering together of the captivity, ſhall begin at thoſe, who are in <hi>America,</hi> therfore <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ilands ſhall truſt in me, and the ſhips of Tarſis</hi> (that is of the ocean) <hi>firſt of all, that they may bring thy ſons from far, and with them, their ſilver, and gold.</hi> They ſhall then come with ſpeed from thoſe countreys, proſtrating themſelves at the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:112444:41"/>mountain of the Lord in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſaith of that redemption in ch. 11.11. <hi>They ſhall come as birds out of Egypt, and as doves out of Aſſyria:</hi> ſo ſaith <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in ch. 60.8. <hi>Who are thoſe that flye as a cloud, and as doves to their neſts?</hi> They which come firſt, ſhall alſo partake of this joy, to ſee others to come to them every moment; for which cauſe the ſame Prophet ſaith, <hi>Lift up thine eyes round about, and behold them who gather themſelves to thee.</hi> And becauſe the two Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſhall firſt of all kindly receive the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and ſhall know the truth, firſt of all embracing the Religion of the Jews, ſacrificing, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God, therfore the Peophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, in ch. 19.25. <hi>Bleſſed be Egypt my people, and Aſſyria the work of my hands; but Iſrael is my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</hi> For ſo thoſe words are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXVIII.</head>
               <p>ALL thoſe are the ſayings of the holy Prophets, from whence doth appear the return of Iſrael into their countrey. It is given to none to know the time thereof, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is revealed to <hi>Rabbi Simeon ben Johay,</hi> the Author of the Zoar; becauſe that God hath reſerved that myſtery to himſelf, as
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:112444:42"/>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is hid with me.</hi> And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> in ch. 63.4. <hi>For the day of vengeance is in my heart, and the yeer in which the redemption ſhall come.</hi> Which the Rabbins thus interpret, <hi>I have reveiled it to my heart, and not to Angels:</hi> and elſwhere, <hi>If any man tels you when Meſſiah ſhall come, believe him not.</hi> So alſo the Angel ſaith to <hi>Daniel,</hi> ch. 12 9. <hi>All things are cloſed up, and ſealed to the time of the end.</hi> Therefore all thoſe, who ſearch after that time, as <hi>Rabbi Seadiah, Moſes Egyptius, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes Gerundenſis, Selomoh Jarchi; Abraham bar Ribi Hijah, Abraham Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo, Mordehai Reato, and Iſaac Abarbanel,</hi> have been miſtaken; for that they would go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond humane capacity, and reveil that, which God concealed. And even to <hi>Daniel</hi> himſelf (to whom was made known the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of the change of the foure Monarchies) it was ſo revealed to him, that he confeſſed he did not underſtand it. Our Ancients did point at this from the letter (m) in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9 7. where he ſaith: <hi>Of the increaſe of his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> which (m) in the Hebrew, being ſuch an (m) which they write only in the end of words, and a cloſe letter, yet is put in the middle of the word, againſt common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe: becauſe that the time of the fifth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy ſhall be hid, till the time when it ſhall begin.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:112444:42"/>
               <head>SECT: XXIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>YEt this I can affirm, that it ſhall be about the end of this age;</hi> and ſo the Prophets ſpeak of that age <hi>about the end of days:</hi> and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many labours, and a long captivity. So <hi>Balaam</hi> prophecies, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.17. <hi>I ſee, but not now; I behold, but not neer; a Star ſhall come out of Jacob.</hi> Iſa. 24.22. <hi>They ſhall be caſt into priſon, and they ſhall be viſited after many days.</hi> And <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.14. <hi>And Sion ſaid, The Lord hath forſaken me, and my Lord hath forgotten me.</hi> Hoſ. 3.4, 5. <hi>The children of Iſrael ſhall be many days without a King, and without a Prince: And after that they ſhall ſeek the Lord their God, and David their King.</hi> The King, and Prophet complains of that delay, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. And after that, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.50.51. he thus concludes, <hi>Remember, O God, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of thy ſervants, who ſuffer ſo many injuries of ſo many people: wherewith they have reproached the ſteps of thy Meſſiah.</hi> As yet at this day it is ſaid, that ALTHOUGH THE MESSIAH WERE LAME, HE MIGHT HAVE COME BY THIS TIME. Though we cannot exactly ſhew the time of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet we judge it to be neer. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. We ſee many prophecies to be fulfilled, and others alſo, which are ſubſervient to a
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:112444:43"/>preparation for the ſame redemption; and it appears by this, that during that long, and ſore captivity, many calamities are fore-told us under the foure Monarchies. <hi>David</hi> ſaith in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 120.7. <hi>Lord, when I ſpeak of peace, they ſpeak of war.</hi> And elſwhere, <hi>We are ſlain all the day for thy name, and are accounted for ſheep which are ſlain.</hi> In <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.7. <hi>He ſhall be led as a ſheep to the ſlaughter, and as a lamb before his ſhearers: he ſhall be dumb, and ſhall not open his mouth.</hi> O how have we ſeen theſe things in the baniſhments of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Spaine!</hi> and how have they proved thoſe crimes, which moſt falſe men have ſaid that ours did commit! Behold they have ſlain them, not for wickedneſſes, which they did not commit, but for their riches which they had. O how have we ſeen all thoſe things done by divine providence, for that thoſe misfortunes for the moſt part hapned on the 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. day of the month <hi>Ab,</hi> an ominous, and unhappy day, on which the firſt, and ſecond Temple were burnt, and the ſpies wept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXX.</head>
               <p>VVHat ſhall we ſay of that horrible monſter, the Spaniſh Inquiſition, what crueltie hath not daily been uſed
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:112444:43"/>againſt a company of miſerable ones, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, old men, and children, of every ſex, and age, who were ſlain, becauſe they could not divine who was their ſecret accuſer? But let us ſee, why in all thoſe places (in which that Spaniſh tyranniaall Empire rules,) they were ſlain, who would obſerve the law of <hi>Moſts;</hi> and by how many, and how great miracles, hath that law been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed? and what unrighteouſneſſe is there in it? We daily ſee examples of conſtancy in ours, worthy of all praiſe, who for the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying of Gods name, have been burnt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live. Truly many who are ſtill living, can witneſſe all thoſe things. In the yeer 1603. At <hi>Lisbone, Diego d'Aſſumeaon,</hi> a Monk of 24. years, was burnt alive, who defended him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Inquiſition againſt ſome, who would have reduced him, to Chriſtianity, who was born a Chriſtian, and made a Jew; which all wondred at; the Inquiſitors being grieved that they had publiſhed the reaſons which he had alleadged, would have recall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their ſentence; but it was then too late; for it was divulged through the world, which I my ſelf have by me. Alſo the Lord <hi>Lope de Vera y Alarcon</hi> deſerves the praiſe of martyrdome, who being born of a noble, and eminent family, and very learned in the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:112444:44"/>Hebrew, and Latine tongues, did imbrace our religion; neither thought it ſufficient to be ſuch himſelf, but diſcovered himſelf to many others; thereupon in <hi>Ann.</hi> 1644. in the 20th. of his age, he being impriſoned at <hi>Valla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolid,</hi> though he lived in the dark, yet he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered light to many; neither could the great number of Doctors, nor the greater af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction of his parents, move him from his enterpriſe, either by tears, or by promiſes. He circumciſed himſelf in priſon (ô ſtrange act, and worthy of all praiſe!) and named him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>beleeving Judas;</hi> and at laſt, as a 2d: <hi>Iſaac,</hi> offered himſelf to the flames, contemning life, goods, and honors, that he might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain immortall life, and good things that cannot periſh; in the 25th. yeer of his age. Now though thoſe were not of the family of Iſrael, yet they obtained an immortall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which is better then this life. Alſo we have many examples of our own, which did equalize them, of which that is one, which is done in our time, and is worthy to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred; <hi>Iſaac Caſtrenſis Tartas</hi> (whom I knew, and ſpoke with) a learned young man, and verſed in the Greek, and Latine; he being but newly come to <hi>Fernambuc,</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the <hi>Portugeſe,</hi> and carried to <hi>Lisbone,</hi> and burnt alive; he was a young man of 24.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:112444:44"/>yeers old; ſcorning riches, and honors, which were offered to him, if he would turn Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. They who ſay he was a traytor, do lye egregiouſly; for he did defend that place where he was Governor, moſt valiantly; as ours do deport themſelves in thoſe fortified places which are committed to their charge. The ſame martyrdome was undergone at <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> by <hi>Eli Nazarenus,</hi> in <hi>Ann.</hi> 1639. <hi>Januar.</hi> 23. who after he had lived 14. whole yeers in priſon, all which time he eat no fleſh, leſt he ſhould defile his mouth; he called him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by that name, after he had circumciſed himſelf. Such a Martyr alſo, this yeer, was <hi>Thomas Therbinon</hi> in the City of <hi>Mexico.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXXI.</head>
               <p>IF the Lord fulfilled his word in calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he will fulfill it alſo in felicities. Therefore <hi>Rabbi Aquibah</hi> laughed, when he ſaith a wolf run out of the Temple being deſtroyed, though his companions wept; he ſaying, Now is fulfilled that prophecie of <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> in <hi>Lament.</hi> 5.18. <hi>And the foxes ſhall walk therein;</hi> and he added, and thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings alſo ſhall follow, which the Lord hath promiſed. We ſee all the curſes of God come to paſſe, which are mentioned in <hi>Levit.</hi> and <hi>Deuteronomy;</hi> as well as thoſe, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:112444:45"/>our being ſcattered to the ends of the earth (which is <hi>Portugal</hi>) and thoſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the calamities of the Inquiſition; and thoſe of our baniſhments, as I have opened in my book, <hi>De termino vita;</hi> from whence it appears, that all the happie prophecies ſhall be fulfilled. And as we have periſhed, ſo alſo ſhall <hi>Bozra</hi> (that is, <hi>Rome</hi>) pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſh. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 34.6.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXXII.</head>
               <p>SEcondly, the argument which we bring from our Conſtancy under ſo many evils, cannot be eluded, that therefore God doth reſerve us for better things. <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Levit.</hi> 26.44. ſaith, <hi>Though they be in the land of their enemies, yet I will not caſt them away, neither will I abhor them to deſtroy them utterly, and to break my covenant with them, for I am the Lord their God.</hi> And truly theſe things are now fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for that in this captivity, and among the many reproaches which we Jews ſuffer, yet many of ours are honourably enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by Princes, with a ſingular affection. So <hi>D. Iſhac Abarbanel,</hi> who comes of <hi>Davids</hi> line, is Counſeller to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Portugall.</hi> By this alſo he hath got a great name, for that he compoſed the differences, which aroſe between the King of <hi>Portugall,</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:112444:45"/>and the Republique of <hi>Venice.</hi> And from that family of <hi>Abarbarnel</hi> (which I note by the by) do proceed my children, by my wifes ſide. And in the houſe of his ſon, <hi>D. Samuel Abarbanel,</hi> and of his wife <hi>Benuenida,</hi> the Lady <hi>Leonora de Toledo,</hi> was brought up at <hi>Naples,</hi> who is the daughter of <hi>D. Peter de Toledo,</hi> the Vice-roy of <hi>Naples;</hi> who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward was married to the moſt eminent Duke <hi>Coſmus de Medicis,</hi> and having obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Dukedome of <hi>Toſcani,</hi> ſhe honoured <hi>Benuenida</hi> with as much honor, as if ſhe were her mother. That peace, which the <hi>Venetians</hi> made with the Emperour <hi>Sultan Selim,</hi> 75. years agone, was made, and ratified by a certain Jew <hi>Don Selomo Rophe,</hi> who was ſent Ambaſſadour to <hi>Venice,</hi> and received with great pomp, by the <hi>Venetians.</hi> At Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople <hi>D. Ben Iaeſe, Anaucas,</hi> and <hi>Sonſiaos</hi> are of great authority with the Turk. In Egypt the Jews were alwayes <hi>Saraph baxas,</hi> and alſo at this day is <hi>D. Abraham Alholn.</hi> Who knows not that <hi>D. Joſephus Naſſi,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Joannes Micheſius,</hi> about the 66. year of the former age, was Duke of <hi>Naccia,</hi> Lord of <hi>Milum,</hi> and of the ſeven Iſlands, of whom ſee <hi>Famian. Strada</hi> in <hi>Hiſtor. Belgic. part.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi> 5. He was raiſed to theſe honours by <hi>Sultan Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim.</hi> As alſo by <hi>Sultan Amurat, Jacob Aben
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:112444:46"/>Jaes,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Alvaro Mendez</hi> was made Governour of <hi>Tyberias;</hi> witneſſe <hi>Boterus</hi> in <hi>Relation. part.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. In <hi>Barbary<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> the Lords <hi>Rutes</hi> were alwaies Governors of <hi>Sekes, Phes,</hi> and <hi>Taradanta.</hi> In <hi>Ann.</hi> 1609, <hi>D. Samuel Palaxe</hi> was ſent Ambaſſador to the States, by <hi>Mulai Zidan</hi> the King of <hi>Maracco.</hi> But he died at the <hi>Haghe</hi> in <hi>Ann.</hi> 1616. And the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> and the Nobles, were at his unerall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> In <hi>Perſia</hi> who knows not of what account they are? There, thirty years ſince <hi>Elhazar</hi> was 2d. to the King, and as it were Governour. Now <hi>David Jan</hi> ſucceeds him, to whom others alſo being joyned, they live in the Court. And that muſt not be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, that when the moſt eminent Duke of <hi>Holſtein</hi> ſent <hi>Otto Burchmannus</hi> Ambaſſador to <hi>Perſia,</hi> in <hi>Ann.</hi> 1635. he deſired commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datory letters from our Jews at <hi>Hamburg,</hi> to them, who (as we have already told you) do live there in the Court, that they would make way there, for him that was a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; that he might diſpatch his affairs. Which was alſo performed. By which mean ours, who are in <hi>Perſia,</hi> diſmiſſed <hi>Burchman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> with rich gifts, and with Letters to the moſt eminent Duke of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> which the 12. Chuzae, or Princes, had ſubſigned. A copy of which Leteers the moſt excellent <hi>D. Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:112444:46"/>Muſſaphia,</hi> one familiar with the Prince, helped me to. Alſo <hi>Claudius Duretus en ſon threſor des langues, fol.</hi> 302. ſaith, that there are almoſt an infinite number of Jews in <hi>Aſia,</hi> eſpecially in <hi>India,</hi> and that King <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chini</hi> is their great favourer. Yea <hi>Linſchotes</hi> ſaith (where he treats of <hi>Cochini</hi>) that they have Synagogues there, and that ſome of them are of the Kings Counſell. At <hi>Prague, Mordocheas Maiſel</hi> had Arms given him by the Emperour <hi>Matthias,</hi> who alſo knighted him. Which honour <hi>Jacob Bathſebah</hi> alſo had, under the Reign of <hi>Ferdinand;</hi> and many other Families are graced with other ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. And in this very captivity (who could think it) they are ſo wealthy, that (Gods providence favouring them) they may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to themſelves a place among the moſt Noble.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXXIII.</head>
               <p>VVHo can enumerate the number of ours, who are renowned by fame, and learning? The learned <hi>R. Moſes bar Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was Phyſician to <hi>Saladin</hi> the King of Ægypt. <hi>Moſes Amon</hi> to the Emperour <hi>Sultan Bajaſeth. Elias M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntalto</hi> to the moſt eminent Queen of France, <hi>Loyſia de Medicis;</hi> and was alſo her Counſellor. At Padua <hi>Elias Cretenſis</hi>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:112444:47"/>read Philoſophy; and <hi>R. Abraham de Balmas,</hi> the Hebrew grammar. And how much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour had <hi>Elias Grammaticus</hi> at <hi>Rome?</hi> And almoſt all the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> honoured with all kinde of honour, <hi>Abraham Kolorni;</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by a letter writ to him by <hi>Thomas Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zoni nella ſua piazza univerſale del mundo. Picus Mirandula</hi> (who uſed to ſay, <hi>That he had but ſmall underſtanding, who only looked after his own things, and not after other mens</hi>) and others, had Hebrew teachers. <hi>David de Pomis</hi> dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated his book to Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fifth, who lovingly, and courteouſly received both the Author, and work. So at this day we ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſirous to learn the Hebrew tongue of our men. Hence may be ſeen that God hath not left us; for if one perſecute us, another receives us civilly, and courteouſly; and if this Prince treats us ill, another treats us well; if one baniſheth us out of his countrey, another invites us by a 1000 priviledges; as divers Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> have done, the moſt eminent King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and the mightie Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> in <hi>Niſſa. And do we not ſee, that thoſe Republiques do flouriſh, and much increaſe in Trade, which admit the Iſraelites?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:112444:47"/>
               <head>SECT: XXXIIII.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOſes</hi> ſaith in his laſt ſong, that God would revenge the blood of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who are ſcattered. And <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith in ch. 2.3. <hi>Iſrael is the Lords holy thing, the firſt fruits of his increaſe; all who devour him ſhall be found guilty; evill ſhall come upon them, ſaith the Lord.</hi> And that the hiſtories of divers times, even from <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> to theſe very times, do teſtifie. Have not the Monarchies of great Princes been deſtroyed? Conſider with me the miſerable ends of <hi>Antiochus,</hi> of <hi>Pompey,</hi> of <hi>Siſibuthus,</hi> of <hi>Philip</hi> the King of <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonſus</hi> the ſon of <hi>John</hi> the 2d. And we may remember, how King <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> with his 4th. generation, and with all his Nobles, was ſlain in a battel of <hi>Africa,</hi> in that ſame place, in which he had cauſed the Jews to be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and <hi>Iſabel</hi> were the great perſecuters of our Nation, but how did both he, and ſhe die? as for him his ſon-in-law, and his own ſubjects did perſecute him; and his onely ſon died (leaving no iſſue) on his wedding-day, being 17. years old. His daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being Heir of the Kingdom, and of her fathers hatred, would not marry to <hi>Emanuel</hi> king of <hi>Portugal,</hi> unleſſe he would compell us to be baniſhed, and change our Religion.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:112444:48"/>But ſhe dyed in child-birth of her ſon <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goci,</hi> and alſo her ſon, before he was half a yeer old; and the ſucceſſion was devolved upon the Kingdom of <hi>Spaine.</hi> It is not long ſince, that the Spaniards exerciſed upon us at <hi>Mantua,</hi> what ever cruelties they could invent; what ſhall we ſay of that, that at <hi>Madrid,</hi> in the yeer 1632. was done by the Inquiſition, the King, and Princes of the Kingdom concurring; but in the very ſame month dyed the Infant <hi>Charles,</hi> and their kingdom declined. What wonder is it if God hath chaſtiſed divers kingdoms by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie wayes: but of this I treat farther in my Hiſtory of the Jews. Let us conclude there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that that good, which God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, will ſhortly come, ſince we ſee that we have ſuffered thoſe evils, which he hath threatned us with, by the Prophets.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXXV.</head>
               <p n="3">3<hi rend="sup">ly,</hi> THe ſhortneſſe of time (when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve our redemption ſhall appear) is confirmed by this, that the Lord hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that he will gather the two Tribes <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Benjamin,</hi> out of the foure quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the world, calling them <hi>Nephuſſim.</hi> From whence you may gather, that for the fulfilling of that, they muſt be ſcattered
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:112444:48"/>through all the corners of the world; as <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> ſaith, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7. <hi>And when the ſcattering of the holy people ſhall have an end, all thoſe things ſhall be fulfilled.</hi> And this appears now to be done, when as our Synagogues are found in <hi>America.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXXVI.</head>
               <p n="4">4<hi rend="sup">ly,</hi> TO theſe, let us adde that, which the ſame Prophet ſpeaks, in ch. 12. ver: 4. <hi>That knowledge ſhall be encreaſed;</hi> for then the prophecies ſhall better be underſtood, the meaning of which we can ſcarce attain to, till they be fulfilled. So after the <hi>Ottoman</hi> race began to flouriſh, we underſtood the prophecie of the two legs of the Image of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> which is to be overthrown by the fifth Monarchy, which ſhall be in the world. So <hi>Jeremiah</hi> after he had handled in Chap. 30. the redemption of Iſrael, and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah, and of the war of <hi>Gog,</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> (of which <hi>Daniel</hi> alſo ſpeaks in ch. 12.) when he treats of the Scepter of the Meſſiah the ſon of <hi>David,</hi> of the ruine of the Nations, of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoration of <hi>Judah,</hi> of holy <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and of the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: Temple, he addes in ver: 24. <hi>The fierce anger of the Lord ſhall not return, till he hath exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted it, and till he hath performed the intents of his heart; in the latter daies ye ſhall underſtand it.</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:112444:49"/>From whence follows what we have ſaid, that the time of redemption is at hand. And becauſe <hi>Jeremiah</hi> in that chapter makes an abridgment of all things that ſhall be, therefore it is ſaid in ver: 2, <hi>Write thee all the words which I have ſpoken to thee, in a book.</hi> By this mean making the prophecie clearer, by relating in a clear ſtyle, what ever the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets had foretold; imitating <hi>Moſes,</hi> the laſt words of whoſe ſong are, <hi>Sing, O ye Nations, with his people,</hi> in <hi>Deut</hi> 32.43. Alſo the laſt words which he ſpoke, after that he had bleſſed the Tribes, are theſe, <hi>Happy art thou, O Iſrael: who is like to thee, O people? ſaved by the Lord, who is the ſhield of thy help, and the ſword of thy excellency; and thine enemies ſhall be found lyars to thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon their high places,</hi> in <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.29. From whence it appears, that God will revenge the blood of Iſrael, which hath been ſhed. <hi>Joel</hi> confirms the ſame in ch. 3.19. <hi>Egypt ſhall be a deſolation, and Fdom ſhall he a filthy deſert, for the violence, and injury offered to the Jews, and becauſe they have ſhed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood in their land.</hi> And as they ſhall be puniſhed by the juſt judgement of God, who wiſh us evill: ſo alſo God will give bleſſings upon them who favour us. And thoſe are the trees of the field which then ſhall rejoyce. So God ſaith to <hi>Abraham,</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3. <hi>I will
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:112444:49"/>bleſſe them who bleſſe thee, and curſe them that curſe thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XXXVII.</head>
               <p>THeſe are the things which I could ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerning this matter, which hath not been heretofore handled; from whence theſe conſequences may be deduced.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the Weſt-Indies, were anciently inhabited by a part of the 10. Tribes, which paſſed thither out of <hi>Tartary,</hi> by the Streight of <hi>Anian.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. That the Tribes are not in any one place, but in many; becauſe the Prophets have foretold their return ſhall be into their Countrey, out of divers places; <hi>Iſaiah</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſaith it ſhall be out of eight.</item>
                  <item>3. That they did not return to the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>: Temple.</item>
                  <item>4. That at this day they keep the Jewiſh Religion.</item>
                  <item>5. That the prophecies concerning their return to their Countrey, are of neceſſitie to be fulfilled.</item>
                  <item>6. That from all coaſts of the world they ſhall meet in thoſe two places, <hi>ſo: Aſſyria,</hi> and <hi>Egypt;</hi> God preparing an eaſie, pleaſant way, and abounding with all things, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, Chap. 49. and from thence they ſhall
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:112444:50"/>flie to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as birds to their neſts.</item>
                  <item>7. That their kingdom ſhall be no more divided; but the twelve Tribes ſhall be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together under one Prince, that is, under <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Son of <hi>David;</hi> and that they ſhall never be driven out of their land.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <head>SECT: XXXVIII.</head>
               <p>I Return to the relation of our <hi>Montezinus,</hi> which I prefer before the opinions of all others, as moſt true. For that <hi>Peru</hi> ſhould be derived from the name <hi>Ophir,</hi> as <hi>Gulielmus Postellus, Goropius in Ortelius, Bozius de ſignis Eccleſ. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3: <hi>Marinus in arcâ Noah, P. Sa. in</hi> 3. <hi>Reg. Pomarius</hi> in his Lexicon, and <hi>Poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Biblioth. c.</hi> 8. do think, cannot be proved; as <hi>Pineda</hi> hath well obſerved, in <hi>Job, c.</hi> 28. <hi>p.</hi> 500. for we have ſaid out of <hi>Garcilaſſo de la Vega,</hi> that that name was unknown to them of <hi>Peru. Ophir</hi> then is Eaſt-India, if we beleeve <hi>Joſephus, lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Antiquit. Judaic. c.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp; Acoſta in lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Hiſtor. Ind.</hi> from whence <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> fetched gold, and precious ſtones. But what <hi>Gomara in part.</hi> 1. <hi>hiſt. Ind. fol.</hi> 120. and <hi>Zarate in proaem. hiſt. Peru,</hi> would have, that ours did paſſe over that famous, and much praiſed Iſland (by <hi>Plato</hi> in <hi>Critia,</hi> and <hi>Timae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>) of <hi>Atlantis,</hi> and ſo went into the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Iſlands of <hi>Barlovent,</hi> and from thence
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:112444:50"/>to the firm land, and at laſt to the kingdom of <hi>Peru,</hi> and <hi>New-Spaine;</hi> it is deſervedly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded as fabulous; and <hi>Acoſta</hi> laughs at it, <hi>in lib.</hi> 1. <hi>hist. Ind. c.</hi> 22. But <hi>Marſilius Ficinus in comment. in Timaeum, c.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; Critia,</hi> that he might defend <hi>Plato,</hi> thinks (and his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, <hi>Porphyry, Origen,</hi> and <hi>Proclus</hi> do follow him) that all that which is in <hi>Critia,</hi> and in <hi>Timaeus,</hi> is to be underſtood allegorically. And who will believe <hi>Leſcarbotus,</hi> who ſaith, that they are the Canaanites, who fled thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for fear of <hi>Joſhua?</hi> For I cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that they ſought out Countreys ſo far remote. They who will have them of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru</hi> to have come out of <hi>Norwey,</hi> or <hi>Spaine,</hi> may be confuted by their very form, manners, and the unlikeneſſe of their languages. But that is more falſe, that they are Iſraelites, who have forgot circumciſion, and their rites. For they are of a comly body, and of a good wit, as ſaith Doctor <hi>Johannes Huarte,</hi> in his book which is called, <hi>Examen ingenior. c.</hi> 14. But contrarily all men know that the Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are deformed, dull, and altogether rude. And we have abundantly ſhown, with how great ſtudy, and zeal, the Iſraelites have kept their language, and Religion, out of their Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:112444:51"/>
               <head>SECT: XXXIX.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOntezinus</hi> then ſpeaks moſt likely; that as other people forced the Iſraelites to betake them to the mountains: ſo <hi>America</hi> being firſt of all inhabited by the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Tartars,</hi> they were driven to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of <hi>Cordillecae,</hi> where at laſt they were hid, as God would have it. Truly, comparing the Iſraelites themſelves, or their laws, with other people, I ſee not any thing that comes nearer truth. Perhaps alſo <hi>America</hi> was not of old contiguous to <hi>Aſia</hi> on the North ſide. It doth not ſeem to me ſuch an abſurdity, to ſay, that the Iſraelites went out of <hi>Tartary</hi> into <hi>America</hi> by land; and afterward, that God, to preſerve his, among other miracles, alſo wrought this, to make that a Sea, where now is the ſtreight of <hi>Anian.</hi> Yea that might be done without a miracle, by accident, as we know that more than once, the Sea by a violent ſtorme hath carried away the Land, and made Iſlands. <hi>Xenophon in ſuis aequivoc.</hi> mentions the inundations of Aegypt, which happened in the dayes of <hi>Prometheus,</hi> and <hi>Hercules.</hi> Alſo <hi>Beroſus in lib.</hi> 5. and <hi>Diodorus li.</hi> 6. mention the inundation of <hi>Attica,</hi> in which <hi>Athens</hi> ſtands. <hi>Pliny in lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 85. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 11. <hi>Strabo in lib.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 12. and <hi>Plutarch</hi> in <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andr.</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:112444:51"/>relate the drowning of the Iſle <hi>Pharao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica;</hi> of which <hi>Luther</hi> ſpeaks ſo elegantly in <hi>lib. ultimo.</hi> Beſide, who knows not how many, and how great Cities have at divers times been almoſt wholly ruined by ſeverall earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes? <hi>Sueton. in Tiberio, c.</hi> 48. writes, that under <hi>Tiberius,</hi> twelve Cities in <hi>Aſia</hi> have been by this mean ruined. <hi>Oroſius lib.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 4. and <hi>Dion Caſſius, lib.</hi> 57. do affirm the ſame, though they differ about the time. <hi>Tacitus in lib.</hi> 14. and <hi>Euſebius in Chron.</hi> relate the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of that famous, and rich City of <hi>Laodicea. Origen tom.</hi> 28. <hi>in Joan.</hi> and <hi>Baronius tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Annal. Eccleſiaſt. Ann.</hi> 340. do ſpeak of other Earthquakes, which have deſtroyed divers, and very many men, and Cities. And <hi>P. Alonſus in ſuo manual tempor.</hi> relates, that the ſame hath happened in our dayes; ſaith he, In the yeer 1638. <hi>a great Earthquake hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in the Iſlands of the Tercerae, but eſpecially in S. Michael, where the Governor dwels; for that unheard of ſhaking of the earth, and houſes ſtruck ſo great a terror into the Inhabitants, that all fled out of their houſes, and lived in the fields; a little after, two miles from thence, they ſaw the Sea vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit up abundance of fiery matter, which made a very thick ſmoak, which covered the very clouds; and it caſt up many great ſtomes, which ſeemed like rocks; part whereof falling down again, made an
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:112444:52"/>Iſland in the Sea, which was half a mile over, and ſixty fathome high, and an hundred and fifty fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thome deep. That hot exhalation which that fiery mountain ſent forth, pierced the very waters, and ſtifled ſo many fiſhes, that two Indian ſhips could not carry them.</hi> The ſame Iſland two yeers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, was ſwallowed up again of the Sea.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
               <head>SECT: XL.</head>
               <p>HE that doth ſeriouſly weigh thoſe things, may (I think) well gather, that the Sea of the Streight of <hi>Anian</hi> was an inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. By affirming which, this doubt may be anſwered, <hi>ſc.</hi> That after the univerſall Flood, man-kinde encreaſed again, and all beaſts, which had been preſerved in the Ark. But how could ſo many kindes of beaſts, (which come by propagation, and are not bred out of the earth,) be found in thoſe Countreys? Some did ſwim thither, ſome were brought thither by ſome huntſmen, ſome were bred out of the earth, as <hi>Av<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> thinks it happened in the firſt Creation. But what Land-beaſt can ſwim over ſo great a Sea? And would Huntſmen carry Lyons thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and other ſuch kinde of beaſts, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to the great hazard of their lives? And if God would have created thoſe beaſts out of the earth, he would not have commanded
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:112444:52"/>
                  <hi>Noah</hi> to have kept them in the Ark. I am fully perſwaded, that the beaſts which are found there, paſſed that way into <hi>America;</hi> unleſſe any thinks that this new world is joyned to the old, on ſome other ſide, as <hi>Herrera</hi> beleeves, <hi>Dec.</hi> 3. <hi>Lib.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
               <head>SECT 42.</head>
               <p>AS for the other things in the relation of our <hi>Montezinus,</hi> they ſay nothing which ſavours of falſhood. For their ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Semah,</hi> truly it is the cuſtome of our people, in what part ſoever of the world they live; and it is the abridgement of the confeſſion, and religion of the <hi>Iewes.</hi> That revelation of the Magicians; whom they call <hi>Mohanes,</hi> it agrees with thoſe things which in 2 <hi>Eſdras,</hi> you may ſee, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Miracles which God wrought for the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> as they paſſed over <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rates,</hi> concerning thoſe conditions of not revealing ſecrets to any, but ſuch an one who hath ſeene three hundred Moones, (which make twenty five yeares) it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares to be true, by what the famous <hi>De Laet</hi> tels, in many parts of <hi>America,</hi> that the <hi>Indians</hi> doe compute their yeares by Moones. That a ſecret muſt be told in the Field, doth not that argue a <hi>Iewiſh</hi> cuſtom,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:112444:53"/>which the ancients have obſerved in <hi>Iacob.</hi> who being about to depart from <hi>Laban,</hi> he called his Wives into the field.</p>
               <p>I now conclude this Diſcourſe, in which this only was in my intention, that I might briefly, and compendiouſly declare mine, and the Rabbies opinion, concerning thoſe things which I have handled. I hope t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> this my endeavour will not be unaccep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, being deſired by many men, famous both for Birth, and for Learning; not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, having therein explained the relation of <hi>Montezinus,</hi> with what brevity I could. The Name of God be bleſſed for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:112444:53"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
